<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise concerning deniall of Christ: a subject of most high concernment for all those who intend to follow Christ. / Written by Christopher Blackwood, an unprofitable servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Blackwood, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 238 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76801</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867171</idno>
  <idno type="VID">119464</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240917441</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E436_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867171</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99867171e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76801)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 69:E436[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise concerning deniall of Christ: a subject of most high concernment for all those who intend to follow Christ. / Written by Christopher Blackwood, an unprofitable servant of Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Blackwood, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Blackmore, at the signe of the Angell in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Divinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew X, 33 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119464:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE CONCERNING DENIALL OF CHRIST: A Subject of most high concernment for all those who intend to follow CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Christopher Blackwood,</hi> an unprofitable Servant of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In English:</hi> Being questioned, we do not deny, accounting it ungodly not to speak truth in all things. <bibl>
                     <hi>Justin Martyr Apol. 1. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum Senatum.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeteris negantibus adhibetis tormenta ad confitendum, solis Christianis ad negandum.</hi> You use torments to others that denie to make them to confesse, but to Christians alone to make them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. <bibl>
                     <hi>Tertul. Apol. adversus Gentes, cap. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Thou holdest fast my name, and hast not denied my faith, even in those dayes wherein Antipas was my faithfull martyr who was slain among you where Satan dwelleth. <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 2.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward Blackmore,</hi> at the signe of the Angell in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119464:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119464:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>OƲt of pity to the soules of many, who in having only a fancy instead of faith, professe that they know God, but in their works or (which is no lesse soule-damning though not so much reproachfull) in the habit and frame of their heart denie him, have I writ these things: he that hath not studied the Crosse of Christ, how notionall so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in his mind, and how glorious soever in his profession, is yet a stranger from the Lord, and hath not aright learned the mysterie of godlinesse: that therefore thou mayest be rightly instructed in the Doctrine of Confession, then which the Gospell knowes few or no points more heard to learne, or more dangerous to be ignorant of, and maist not ship-wrack thy faith and conscience, I have like one that narrowly hath escaped Ship-wrack, discovered unto thee a dangerous unseen Rock, whereon thousands split their soules for ever, and these none of the worst men and women, but such as have escaped the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the world, too good to goe to hell, and yet not good enough to goe to heaven: to fathom that deep abysse of vaine feares, Idoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of creatures, trechery against Christ, cowardlinesse in good cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, dissimulation in worship, regulation of conscience by humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, backe-sliding in heart, with many other evills, which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany habituall deniall of Christ, is beyond my line and plummet, yet have I waded a little, being guided I trust, by the Map of Divine Light, to make some discovery of these Rocks: This subject of deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of Christ is something unknowne, forasmuch as I never read or heard of any Treatise about the same in print, and therefore it will not be amisse to cast an eye upon it, I trust through the guidance of that good Spirit of grace, and through the experience of my owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull heart, I have (though not so fully as were to be wished) given some light in this point, hoping that God will stirre up some more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to make further discoveries herein: when evill times come, no sin is wont more deeply to afflict then that we have denied him, of whom we desire then to be owned. And nothing more credits the cause of God, then for the people of God to be willing to witnesse the same with
<pb facs="tcp:119464:3"/> the losse of all earthly comforts; this was that which wrought so much upon <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> about <hi>1500.</hi> yeares ago; hear his words, in his first Apologie, p. <hi>39.</hi> to the Romane Senate, <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. for I my selfe being a follower of the Doctrine of <hi>Plato,</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Christians accused slanderously, and seeing that they went without feare to death, and to all other things which are counted terrible, I thought with my selfe it was impossible that they should live in wickednesse, and love of pleasures; for what lover of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, or intemperate person, or that delights to feed upon mans flesh, can willingly entertaine death, or will suffer the losse of his goods, and will not rather by all meanes seeke to prolong his life, and by lying hid, deceive Princes, that he may not deliver himselfe up to be put to death.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas there are in this Treatise some Historicall Narrations and Confirmations out of Antiquity, I shall desire the Reader, not to mis-interpret that which was intended for thine and mine owne spiritualll good, so farre as my own heart can judge: my scope herein was partly to let thee see that this Doctrine was no new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but such as (besides the testimony of Scriptures) the practice of Saints in sundry ages commended unto us, and partly to delight thee by mingling profit and pleasure together, that whiles thou conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest the sweetnesse of the words, thou mayest also consider the truth and weightinesse of the point in hand, that God hereby may bring over thy heart to an habituall intention to confesse Christ with the losse of all thou hast; and partly that a point of such concernment may not be sleighted through the Authours superficiall handling thereof. If God shall do thy poor soul any good hereby I have my end, but if not, take heed this Treatise be not a witnesse against thee in the great-day of the Lord. I shall desire no more of thee, Reader, save (if thou canst pray) that I may have thy prayers to our God to perfect and stablish the same in me, which I commend unto thee, least whiles I preach to others to confesse the Lord, I my self be found a back-slider in heart or profession; I have no more at present, save that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Lords and his Churches devoted (though unprofitable) Servant. <hi>Christopher Blackwood.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119464:3"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF THE DENIALL OF CHRIST.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTHEW. 10.33.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Whosoever shall deny me before men, him will I deny before my Father which is in Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hrist had foretold sundry evills which should befall his Disciples for his cause, the last whereof was death; against the four former, having propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed sundry Consolations; as when they should be brought before Councels and Governors, the Spirit should teach them what to answer, <hi>ver.</hi> 17.18, 19, 20. and when they should suffer the hatred, not only of near kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, but of all men, (if notwithstanding the hatred of the world they did persevere) they should be saved, <hi>ver.</hi> 21.22. and when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119464:4"/> their enemies should persecute them from City to City, God would still provide a harbor for them among the spiritual <hi>Israel</hi> of God, till the second coming of Christ. <hi>ver.</hi> 23. And whereas the Adversaries would reproach them, and call them dogs, Heritecks, nay, Devils, for their comfort, it was no more then was done to the master of the house, whom they called <hi>Belzebub. ver.</hi> 24.25. Now Christ having comforted his Disciples against these evils, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained one more, yea, the greatest evil of all to be comforted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, even death it self, which some of them must look for, and all of them must prepare for, if they preacht upon the house tops that which he spake unto them in the eare; therefore, that they might be better able to encounter with this terrible of terribles; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them in general, fear them not, therefore, <hi>ver.</hi> 26.27. but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause fear is a most wakeful affection, as being conversant about danger, and so much the more wakeful, when it beholds death, and will hardly be cast out by three or four words; hence Christ pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds four grounds to stay their hearts: First, from the limited power of the enemies, they can only touch the body, they cannot touch the soul. <hi>ver.</hi> 28. Secondly, from the Providence of God, the enemies cannot touch an hair of our heads, but as God permits, much less can they touch our lives, without his permissive and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing Providence; a sparrow cannot fall to the ground, much less can your lives, which are more valued with God then many spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows. <hi>ver.</hi> 29.30, 31. Thirdly, the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> ground is from the promise made to those, that notwithstanding the Adversary shall threaten death, yet they are resolved to confess the truth; unto these Christ saith, <hi>He that confesseth me before men, him will I confess before my Father in Heaven.</hi> Fourthly, the fourth ground from the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>He that denies me,</hi> though to save his life, <hi>him will I deny before my Father in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words, avoyding curiosities, are two things considerable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An universal admonition, that no man venture upon this sin of denial of Christ; <hi>Whosoever shall deny me before men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A terrible Commination, <hi>him will I deny before my Father which is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To open the words, three questions must be resolved.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Quest.</hi> What it is to deny Christ?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> Denial presupposes a question, which admits a double an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, either affirmative, which we are bound to make; or negative, which we are forbid; now when we shall (either to escape per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119464:4"/> and the Cross, or to obtain earthly enjoyments and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,) deny those principles which we in our hearts are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced are Gods Truth, this is flat denial of Christ.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Quest.</hi> What denial of Christ is here meant in the Text, which excludes a man out of Heaven?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> There is a two-fold denial of Christ; 1. Actual, when a man, in some vehement tentation of fear or danger, doth once, or oftner, deny Christ, yet in the habit of his heart doth cleave to Christ, yea, and to that truth, which for the present he doth deny: So <hi>Peter</hi> denied Christ again and again, and yet he is in Heaven: So <hi>Bilney</hi> abjured the truth, and subscribed his abjuration. <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 265. Yet after this abjuration, as the Historian sets down, <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 271. The said <hi>Bilney,</hi> after much conflict of conscience, for a whole years space, <q rend="margQuotes">wherein he thought all the Scriptures were against him, and sounded to his condemnation; yet after God endued him with such strength, that he not only confessed the faith, but suffered his body to be burned for the same.</q> The same is related of <hi>Thomas Benbridg</hi> Gentleman, Martyr, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon, vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 884. <q rend="margQuotes">who feeling the intolerable heat of the fire, cryed out, I recant; but before he was taken from the stake, Doctor <hi>Seaton</hi> wrote Articles to have him subscribe to, as touching the Pope, Sacrament, &amp;c. to which with much pain and grief of heart he subscribed; being in prison, he wrote a Letter to Doctor <hi>Seaton,</hi> and recanted those words he spake at the stake, unto which he had subscribed, being grieved that ever he did sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe them: Whereupon, expressing his conscience, he was the same day seven night after burnt, where the vile tormentors did rather broyl him then burn him.</q>
               <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 885. These men, and many others, though through weakness and fear they denyed the truth with <hi>Peter,</hi> yet afterwards with the same <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 4.9. confess the same before whole counsess.</p>
            <p>Contrary, there have been actual confessions of truth by many men, who yet shall never enter Heaven; when times have been peaceable, so that the Gospel and peace have gone hand in hand; so <hi>Spira</hi> and Doctor <hi>Dentleton,</hi> and others, have confessed truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is an habitual denyal of Christ, when a man in the bent and frame of his heart, hath an intention in himself, that rather then he will leave such a dwelling, or estate, or friend, or credit, or suffer such an imprisonment, banishment, dismembring or death, he will (if he cannot evade by distinction, and so craftily come off) (which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119464:5"/> is no less guilt in the sight of God, though less reproach in the sight of man) flatly deny, that which in his heart he acknowledgeth to be the eternal truth of God; many men must needs acknowledg this an horrible sin, but few think themselves to live in this sin; and yet give me leave to tell you, that most men, where the sound of the Gospel is, live in this sin, though not explicitely to have such an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention exprest in the mind, yet implicitely, because they have not an habitual intention to leave all that is dear unto them for the Lord; they do not say in their hearts, they will not leave all rather then deny the truth; neither do they say in their hearts, they will leave all rather then deny the truth, but imbrace the truth at rovers, without any determination at all, what to do in point of confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the former, I mean, actual denial of Christ, though it may, and commonly doth, fill the conscience of the person that falls into it with horror and anguish; yet doth it not exclude a man out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but this habitual denial which remains in most souls with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no anguish, and may (and too often doth) remain in persons that have made a large and a long profession, excludes out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and this is the denial I take to be meant here in the Text.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Quest.</hi> How will Christ deny those that habitually deny him on Earth?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> When they shall desire to be acknowledged among the sheep at the day of judgment; Christ will not only deny them, but also be ashamed of them. <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38. It was a speech of one <hi>Godtes Calchus, I am affraid to deny the truth, lest hereafter I should be denyed of the truth.</hi> When they shall say, Lord we have prophesied in thy name, and in thy name cast out Devils, he wil say, I know you not; when they shall say, as the foolish Virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, Lord, Lord, open to us, he wil say, depart, I know you not; when they shall say, I was baptized in thy name, I was a professor of thy truth, I preacht, I printed for thee; true will Christ say, but for all this thou must depart among the workers of iniquity; for thou didst not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny my cause at such a time, and such a place, but also often, yea, hadst thou lived ever, thou wouldest ever have denyed me, mightest thou have got gain, or escaped punishment by thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of me; therefore, thou being a back-slider in heart shalt be filled with the fruit of thine own ways. <hi>Proverbs Chap.</hi> 14. <hi>verse</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>The words being thus opened, I shall observe one point from them, that is,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119464:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Observ.</hi> Those that do habitually deny Christ or his Truth, Christ wil deny them before his Father in Heaven, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. If we deny him he wil also deny us. Actual denial of Christ is dangerous, though it be but one time, especially when the soul hath time to deliberate, so that God for such an action is wont to fil the conscience with horror, that persons would give all the world to be eased of it; how much more dangerous is habitual denial? See an example of one, and some fear of both these, in <hi>Francis Spira,</hi> who being called before <hi>John Casa,</hi> the Popes Legat, for preaching That we must wholy and only depend on the free and unchangeable love of God in the death of Christ as the only way to salvation, and for condemning the received rites of the Romish Church; and in a word, accused for a dangerous <hi>Lutheran: Spira</hi> seeing the storm hanging over his head, having had a grievous combat betwixt the Spirit of God suggesting the the danger of denial, and the flesh suggesting the loss of substance and credit, and the terror of prisons and death; the flesh geting the upper hand he went to the Legat at <hi>Venice,</hi> and salutes him with this news; <q rend="margQuotes">Having for these divers years entertained an opinion concerning some Articles of Faith contrary to the orthodox and received judgment of the Church, and uttered many things against the Authority of the Church of Rome, and universal Bishop; I humbly acknowledg my fault and error, and my folly in misleading others: I therefore yeeld my self in all obedience to the supream Bishop, into the bosom of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> never to depart again from the traditions and decrees of the holy See: I am heartily sorry for what is past, and I humbly beg pardon for so great an offence. The Legat perceiving him to faint, pursues him to the utmost, causeth a recitation of all his Errors to be drawn in writing, together with the confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion annext to it, which accordingly he did; then the Legat com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands him to return to his own town; and there to acknowledg this his confession, and to acknowledg the whole doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be holy and true, and to abjure the opinions of <hi>Luther,</hi> which <hi>Spira</hi> promised to do: but whiles he was on-ward in his journey, he thought he heard a voyce speaking to him in this manner, hast thou unhappy man given thy hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing to the Legat at <hi>Venice?</hi> See thou do not seal it in thine own Country: Dost thou prefer this present life before an eternal? Dost thou wel in preferring wife or children before Christ? Is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119464:6"/> the windy applause of people better indeed then the glory of God; and the possession of this worlds good more dear to thee then the salvation of thine own soul? Is the smal use of a moment of time more desireable then eternal wrath is dreadful? Thou canst not answer for what thou hast done already; nevertheless the gate of mercy is not quite shut: Take heed that thou heapest not sin up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sin, lest thou repent when it wil be too late. Notwithstanding all this warning, being arrived in his own Country, partly through the advice of friends who counseled him in no wise to betray his wife and children, seeing that by so smal a matter as the reciting of a little schedule, which might be done in less then half an hour, he might free himself from present danger, and preserve those that depended upon him; and partly for other carnal reasons he offers himself to the Praetor, and next morning desperately enters into the publike Congregation; where Mass being finished in the presence of neer upon 2000 people, he recites that infamous abjuration, formerly made at <hi>Venice,</hi> word for word: then was he sent home, restored to his dignities, goods wife &amp; children: But no sooner was he departed but he thought he heard a direful voyce, saying to him thus, Thou wicked wretch thou hast denyed me, thou hast renounced the Covenant of thy obedience, thou hast broken thy vow; hence Apostate, bear with thee the sentence of thy eternal damnation: from which time forwards he never found any peace or ease mind, but continuing in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessant torments, he professed he was captived under the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging hand of the great God; that he heard continually that fearful sentence of Christ that just Judg; that he knew he was utterly undone; that he could neither hope for grace, nor Christs intercession in his behalf: — and after, <hi>pag.</hi> 41. saith, My sin is greater then the mercy of God; — for I willingly and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst knowledg denyed Christ, and I feel that he hardens and wil not suffer me to hope. One asking him whether he did not beleeve that doctrine to be true he had denyed: He answered, I did beleeve it when I did deny it, but now I neither beleeve that nor the doctrine of the Roman Church; When some applied the mercy of God to him, <hi>pag.</hi> 43. he answered, it is exceeding large to the Elect, but not to me who am sealed up to wrath: When some, <hi>pag.</hi> 48. whispered that he was possessed, he said, doubt you of it? I have a whole legion of devils that take up their dwellings within me, and possess me as their own; and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119464:6"/> justly too, for <hi>I HAVE DENYED CHRIST.</hi> Also, <hi>pag.</hi> 55. I tel you there was never such a monster as I am, never was man alive a spectacle of such exceeding misery: I knew that Justification was to be expected by Christ, and I denyed and abjured it, to the end I might keep this frail life from adversity, and my children from poverty; and now behold how bitter life is unto me, and God only knows what shal become of Family, but surely no good is likely to betide it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> After <hi>pag.</hi> 65. he saith, When I, at <hi>Venice,</hi> did first abjure my profession, and so, as it were, drew an Indenture, the Spirit of God often admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisht me, and when at <hi>Citadella</hi> I did, as it were, set to my seal, the Spirit of God often suggested to me, Do not write <hi>Spira,</hi> do not seal; yet I resisted the Holy Ghost and did both, and at that very present I did evidently find a wound inflicted in my very wil; so although I can say I would beleeve, yet can I not say I wil beleeve; God hath denyed me the power of wil, and it befals me in this my miserable estate, as with one that is fast in irons; his friends pity his estate, and perswade him to shake off his fetters, and to come out of his bonds, which he would fain do, but cannot; this is my very case; you perswade me to beleeve; how fain would I do it, but cannot, Oh I cannot. After <hi>pag.</hi> 122. he saith, My heart is estranged from God, I cannot cal him Father from my heart, all good motions are quite gone, my heart is ful of malediction, hatred and blasphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God; I find I grow more and more hardened in heart, your prayers for me shal turn to your own benefit, they can do me no good.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you see, in this example, how God, being a Spirit, hath great influence upon our spirits, and can fil them with invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible horror for denying him; though a man in some cases of theft be not hanged, yet he may be so whipt or burnt in the hand, that he may have little joy in it; so, though a man be not damned for denying Christ in some particular act, yet he may be so fil'd with horror of conscience, that he may thereby become a terror to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and perhaps to all his friends.</p>
            <p>Reasons of the point are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Because those that deny Christ are ashamed of him, they cast an imputation upon his truth, as if it were not worthy to be owned; now, if we now be ashamed of Christ for the present, no wonder if he be ashamed of us hereafter: <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119464:7"/> shal be ashamed of me, and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, of him also shal the Son of man be ashamed, when he cometh in the glory of his Father, with the holy Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Because those that do habitually deny Christ, go on in a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose of sin, they live and dye in a purpose of sin; now a purpose of sin is punished with rejection from Christ: If we walk in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, we have no fellowship with Christ, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.6. Now that those that so deny Christ live in a purpose of sin, appears, because, if conscience or any other propound this question unto them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil you comply to such an idolatrous or superstitious practise, or suffer the dis-inheriting of a father, or the imprisonment of your body? The soul wil be ready to answer, No; when the question is propounded, whether wil you worship a golden image, or be cast into a fiery furnace? The soul shal answer, I cannot burn. When the question is put, whether wil you deny the truth of which you are fully convinced, or go into banishment? The soul shal say, let me chuse iniquity rather then this affliction, <hi>Job</hi> 36.21. When it is thus with you, you live in a purpose of sin. And as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suredly Christ wil deny you, and in this soul-damning purpose to deny Christ for the escaping of crosses, and for the holding of earthly injoyments, the most men in the world live. And under this notion, I mean not only Pagans, Mahumetans, Papists and prophane persons, but even thousands of those who are not a little refined, but are seemingly clean escaped from those that live in Error. Now persons that live in a purpose of sin, Christ wil renounce them; <hi>Psal.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Thou art not a God that hast pleasure in wickedness; neither shal evil dwel with thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third reason is from the rule of equality; Is it equal that when we have renounced Christ here, or denyed him, that he should acknowledg us in Heaven? Is it equal that we should reign with him, when we would not suffer with him? No, but its equal that those that have denyed him should be denyed by him: <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. <hi>Those that have followed me</hi> (through thick and thin) <hi>in the regeneration,</hi> these shal sit upon thrones. When a battel hath been fought, and the General rewards every mans deserts, is it equal that cowardly run-aways shal share therein? Hence the Apostle, to deter the Hebrews from denial and apostacy, saith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38. <hi>If any man draw back, my soul shal have no pleasure in him:</hi> Many men are like slothful servants, who tarry
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119464:7"/> all the year with their matters until harvest come, and then run away or like cowardly Souldiers, who tarry with their Captain ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he batte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be to be fought and then draw back; or like unruly Steers, who when the yoke is to be put upon their neck, draw back, and will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it; if any of these ways thou drawest back, its equal Christ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thee, nor will his soul have pleasure in thee.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Because as Conquerors are only under the promises, so conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed persons are under the threatnings; Conquerors are under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.7. <hi>He that overcometh shall eate of the tree of life, which is in the midst of the Paradise of God;</hi> that is, shall feed for ever on Christ, who was signified by that tree of life: now, what is it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome but this, to confess the Truth of God, notwithstanding the threats of men and devils, though we lose life and liberty for the same? A man is not overcome when he is cast into prison, or banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or loses his life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36, 37. When they were killed all the day long, yet were they Conquerors; but a man is overcome, when for the saving of his estate, limbs, liberty or life, he relinquishes the truth, and denies it: so they that overcome have the joy of the Holy Ghost, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17, <hi>To him that overcomes will I give to eate of the hidden Manna.</hi> Persons that have been combating with some great tentation, and have got victory, have comfort which tastes as sweet to the soul as the manna did to the taste, but is hid from others, as the manna in <hi>Aarons</hi> pot was from the sight of men.</p>
            <p>Again, they that overcome have a sentence of absolution, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.17. <hi>To him that overcometh will I give the white stone, and in the stone a new name written, which no man knoweth saving he that receiveth it.</hi> Christ speaks after the manner of judgments which were used in times past, where two sorts of stones, white and black, were put into two p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tchers, the guiltless were absolved, having their names written in the white stones; the guilty were condemned, having their names written in the black: so persons, that notwithstanding the rage of persecutors overcome, they have a sentence of absolution in their own consciences; this being written and ascertained to them by Gods Spirit, no man knows it, save themselves.</p>
            <p>Again, He that overcometh, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.12. God promiseth to make him an unmoveable Pillar in the Temple of God, meaning, both in grace and glory: And as the <hi>Romans,</hi> and others, had Statues or Pillars wherein their noble exploits were written, so shall these Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors that confess Christ, they shall have written upon them the Name of God, that is, they shall be called Children of God, also the Name of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119464:8"/> the City of God, which is new <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> that is, they shall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>zens of Heaven, also, they shall have Christs new Name, that is, they shall be clothed with glory, as he was after his Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Now, as Conquerers are under promises, so are conquered persons under threats, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. Fearful men lead in the forefront of Hell; these dare not do duty for fear of danger: most men fear Princes and their prisons, more then God and his Hell: As we see <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.7. <hi>As soon as ever they heard the voice of the Cornet, Flute, &amp;c. they fell down and worshiped.</hi> And hence for their fearfulness of men, and their treacher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us denying of the truth caused thereby, God, after their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are destroyed, casts their souls into hel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ʋse.</hi> 1. Reprehension of many persons who habitually deny Christ; many say true, such things are bad, but the Law commands: I say to thee, if thou resolvest to go no further in Religion then the Laws of men permit, thou hadst as good forswear the Gosp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l; If Governors should alter an hundred times, they would alter their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or at least their outward practises as oft; Is not God Lord of the Conscience, and <hi>must we not obey God rather then man? Acts</hi> 4.19..</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if I do not comply, I shall expose my family to hazard, my s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lf to cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l adversaries, poor dyet, low d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> But (though this doth not always fall out) what if it were so? Better do any thing then sin; remember <hi>Moses</hi> chose af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions with Gods People before <hi>Aegypts</hi> Pleasures; the meanest estate accompanied with Gods Love, is better then Princes fare and a wounded conscience.</p>
            <p>Now of those that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Christ, some do it
<list>
                  <item>1. Silently.</item>
                  <item>2. Others do it Expresly.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Silently, when persons from time to time can hear the Truth of God spoken against, his servants rayled on, and Idolatry and Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cryed up and practised, and they sit still, as if the thing nothing concerned them for all they are able to speak in Gods behalf; they are afraid least in speaking they should lose their correspondencies with such companions; now they cannot do their duty, and hold in with them, and therefore they will be si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent: Against this sinful silence, see the carriage of <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 119.46. <hi>I will speak of thy Testimony before Kings, and will not be ashamed.</hi> Though <hi>Jehosaphat</hi> was but too cold, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.8. (though a good man) yet when <hi>Ahab</hi> in words profest a visible hatred against <hi>Micaiah, Jehosaphat</hi> could not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119464:8"/> but justifie the Prophet to the Kings face, using these words, <hi>let not the King say so:</hi> So Christ, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Wisdom is justified of her children:</hi> Shall <hi>Baal</hi> have 400 to plead for him, and God not one <hi>Eliah?</hi> There must be an account given for sinful silence, as well as for wicked speech. It's none of our least sins, that by our sinful silence we have left so many in circumstantial, yea, which is more, in funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental errors. Nothing is more dangerous to God, and destructive to our brethren, then not to declare with our tongues the truth which we beleeve in our hearts, time, places, persons and circumstances being duly weighed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Christ is denied Expresly; and that</p>
            <p n="1">1. In a Vicious life; when our practise doth not answer our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.16. <hi>They profess they know God, but in works they deny him, being abominable, disobedient.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Denying the Lord that bought them: These have a form, but deny the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. These turning the Doctrine of free grace into lascivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness, <hi>deny the only Lord God, and our Lord Jesus,</hi> Jude 4. <q rend="margQuotes">Too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny live the lives of Heathens, under the name of Christians; such there were in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time; <hi>Pamelius,</hi> in his life, complains, that not only very many of the Clergy (to use his word) forsook the faith of Christ for fear of torments, but also confessors, that had once confest Christ, spotted their glory with a wicked life; persons that live wickedly will never confess Christ with loss of their lives.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Christ is Expresly denied in word; when Magistrates shall ask us concerning our faith, and we shall not acknowledg, but for fear of prisons or death deny what we beleeve to be truth. It was a speech of <hi>Spira,</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Christ will not be denied in word, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>refore it is enough that I have denyed him in word, though in heart I never denyed him: He added, it's no small matter to deny Christ, and yet it's more ordinary then men do conceive; it is not only a denyal or abjurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made before the Magistrate, as it is with me; for as often as a Christian doth dissemble a known truth, so often as he approves of false worship by presenting himself at it, so oft he denies Christ.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I may add to his words, how many in private conference deny Christ, whiles for fear of men they deny those truths they inwardly acknowledg? As we are not to deny our sins, but freely confess them before God, so we are to confess the truth before men, though we know before hand, that in so doing, bonds and afflictions in every place abide us.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Famous was <hi>Luther</hi> herein. It is my duty (saith he) and the duty
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119464:9"/> of a Christian to speak the truth, and deny falsehood, against all noise of titles and dignities. I am a Divine, and born in the Kingdom of Truth, and therefore am bound, not only to affirm it, but also to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it by life or death.</q>
               <hi>Clas.</hi> 3. <hi>loc.</hi> 20. <hi>digest. per fabricium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is one of the noblest actions of a Christian, to confess Christ and his Truth before the world, to confess him in the midst of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; neither is it sufficient to confess Christ in word in a corner; but in the Assemblies of Princes and Counsels, we must freely speak our mind, and bear witness to the truth; few indeed dare do this, but this is our duty. Famous were <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> herein, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.8, 9, 10. who witnessed the truth, being filled with the Holy Ghost, though <hi>Peter</hi> formerly denyed Christ before a silly Damosel, yet now when <hi>Annas</hi> the high Priest, and <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> and others were gathered together in counsel, and ask't them by what power or name they did what they did, they answered very couragiously, in these words, <q rend="margQuotes">Be it known unto you all, that by the Name of Jesus Christ of <hi>Nazareth, WHOM YE CRƲCIFIED,</hi> whom God raised from the dead, doth this man stand before you whole.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Only let us desire with <hi>Luther,</hi> who said, <q rend="margQuotes">our knowledg suffers us not to keep silence, and the world suffers us not to speak; it is needful therefore that we be strengthned with the Spirit, that to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scape dangers, we refrain not from confession.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Quaere,</hi> Whether Christ be not denyed in our estates, when his cause calls for something that we have, and we will part with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; the Lord hath need of our Ass, but we will not let him go, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.3. When the cause of God stood in need, they parted with their gold and silver, pleasant things, and precious jewels, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.7, 8, 9. The question at Christs Tribunal will be too many men; didst not thou remember that such a year my cause lay at stake, and thou wouldst do nothing for me? It is all one with many, (as in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb) whether the Dog bite the Bear, or the Bear the Dog; whether the Churches stand or fall; <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Merosh</hi> was curst, because they came not to help the Lord against the mighty.</q>
               <hi>Judges</hi> 5.23.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Christ is denyed in writing; when we shall subscribe to any writing, as truth, which we are perswaded is an error. Divers of the Martyrs, through weakness, having thus subscribed to recantations, in horror of conscience, getting a sight of such recantations, tore the same, and yeilded themselves to the persecutors. Thus doubtless <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rengarius</hi> sundry times denyed the truth; who holding that the bread and wine in the supper being consecrate, are not changed, but remain
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119464:9"/>
               <q rend="margQuotes">in their substances,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 19. <hi>Mon. vol.</hi> 2 <hi>p.</hi> 457, 458.</note> having a certain resemblance or similitude of those things whereof they be Sacraments, meaning of the body and blood of Christ signified thereby, yet after recanted the same, first, under Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth, about the year 1060. After the death of <hi>Leo,</hi> being stung in conscience, he did again acknowledg the truth which he before had denyed. Then Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the second, called him in question for his Tenets, and made him read, and publikely profess before the people a recantation drawn in form of words, which acknowledgment was as much as subscription, wherein he beleeved, that bread and wine after consecration, are not only a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but also are the true body and blood of Jesus Christ, and are sensibly felt, and broken with hands, and chewed with teeth, and withall swore, that if ever he preached or taught against the same, he would endure the severity of the Canons. Some report that once more he denyed under Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> those things which were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by him under Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the second for fear of burn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing; as <hi>Du Plessis</hi> saith in his fourth Book of the Mass, Chap. 8. where the story is at large; some add, that dying, he should say, to day Christ will appear unto me according to my penitentness,</q> as I hope, unto glory, or because of others unto pain, meaning the fears (as I suppose) which lay upon him for such deliberate denying of the truth.</p>
            <p>This was the unhappiness of Doctor <hi>Cranmer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts and Mon. vol. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>666, 667.</hi>
               </note> that he thus denyed the truth, by subscribing to a recantation,<q rend="margQuotes"> when the Papists by fraud and flattery drew him upon hope of life to subscribe a recantation against his conscience. Hear his own words: And now I am come to the great thing that troubleth my conscience more then any thing that ever I did or said in my whole life, and that is the setting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad of a writing contrary to the truth;<note place="margin">Pag. 670. 671. <hi>Ibid</hi>
                  </note> which now here I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, and refuse, as things written with my hand, contrary to the truth which I thought in my heart, and written for fear of death, and to save my life, if it might be, and that is all such bills and papers which I have written or signed with mine hand since my degrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein I have written many things untrue. And forasmuch as my hand offended, writing contrary to my heart, my hand shall first be punished, therefore may I come to the fire, it shal be first burned: in token of the detestation of which fact, <hi>viz.</hi> his subscribing to the denial of the truth, (besides the profession of the contrary to what he had subscribed,) when the fire began to burn near him, stretching out his arm, he put his right hand into the flame, which he held so sted<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ast and unmoveable, saving that once with the same hand he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119464:10"/> wiped his face, that all men might see his hand burned before his body was touched: oftentimes he repeated his unworthy right hand, so long as his voyce could suffer him.</q> If to these examples, we add the recantation subscribed by <hi>Spira,</hi> together with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable anguish of conscience that followed thereupon; every man may tremble to venture upon denial of Christ, by writing and subscription.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Quere.</hi> Whether or no Christ is not denyed in Worship, when we present our selves at such worship as we loath in our hearts? <hi>Hos.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Let the men that Sacrifice kisse the Calves.</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams Priests in sign of conformitie, required that all that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed should kisse the calves, now kissing is a token of love, so that hereby they s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gnified their love to the Calve-worship; now Idolatrous kissing in this kind is cal'd a deniall of God, <hi>Job</hi> 31.27.28. If my mouth hath kissed my hand: — I should have denyed the God that is above; so that its cleer, Idolatrous wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship denyes the true God: but the question is about the presence at such worship, whether that be a denyall of Christ? It seemeth so to be (whiles things manifestly false in their conscience, and that not in smaller, but fundamental points, goe for truth by their silence, they not testifying against them.) Yea after illumination, when a man knows what worship is pleasing to God, yet for fear of losse of goods and friends, he will practise what he knows is not of God; unlesse a man should go thereto with an habit to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test against it; as in the reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the sixth, <q rend="margQuotes">one <hi>William Gardiner,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 16. <hi>Mon. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 744. 745 .746.</note> Merchant of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> being at the City of <hi>Lisbon</hi> in <hi>Portugal,</hi> resolved to go to the Masse (and it was a more then ordinary Masse, for the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> was there present with many great Estates, it being the Sabbath next after his sons mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with the King of <hi>Spains</hi> daughter) when the Cardinall that consecrated it was in the midst of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s feats, tossing the host round about the Challice, making certain circles; the said <hi>Gardiner</hi> ran speedily unto the said Cardinall, and in the presence of the King and Nobles, snatcht away with one hand the cake from the Priest and trod it under his feet, and with the other hand over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the Challice, for the which action he having prepared himself with much prayer day &amp; night, continued perseverantly, testifying against their superstitions and abominations, with much patience of spirit, notwithstanding those unheard of torures which day after day they tortured him with. Another of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119464:10"/> Saints being at Masse in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, cryed out. That if there were any of the Servants of God present, they should bear him witnesse at the day of judgement, that he did not comply to that abominable Idoll of the Masse.</q> So we find the worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.39. crying out in opposition to <hi>Baal, The Lord he is the God, the Lord he is the God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all the difficulty is about hearing: whether persons hearing things manifestly false a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainst points of Faith, which they judge fundamentall shall not by their silence, they not testifying against them, in some measure deny Christ?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Answ.</hi> I wil in this difficult question leave others to their light; onely I say, to me, in my conscience, it would be a denial of Christ, which I am drawn so to think, because every child of wisdom is bound to justifie wisdome, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.19. and to defend the rest of the Hearers from seducement in things that are fundamentally destructive: Its a good speech of <hi>Luther</hi> to <hi>Staupicius;</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Let me be found proud, covetous, an adulterer, and guilty of all faults, so that I be not reproved for wicked silence.</q> There is a notable speech of a Scorch Martyr, who suffered in the raign of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, <hi>Acts and Mon. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 615. <q rend="margQuotes">his name was <hi>Robert Lamb:</hi> one Fryer <hi>Spence</hi> preaching at <hi>Perth,</hi> that prayer made to Saints was so necessary, that without it there could be no hope of Salvation; which blasphemous doctrine a Burgesse of the said town, called <hi>Robert Lamb,</hi> hearing, could not abide, but accused him in open audience of erroneous doctrine, and adjured him in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods Name to utter the truth; for which fact of interrupting the said Fryar, the said <hi>Robert Lamb</hi> was accused, which he not only confessed, but also affirmed constantly; that it was the duty of no man which understood and knew the truth, to hear the same im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned without contradiction; and therefore, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
                  </label> sundry which there were present in judgment, who hid the knowledg of the truth, should bear their burden in Gods presence for consenting to the same, <hi>hac ille;</hi>
               </q> This was the chief thing brought against this godly Martyr, even the witnessing against this false doctrine, for which he lost his life.</p>
            <p n="6">6 There is a denyal of Christ in not asserting principles, which is, when we know such a thing is a truth, but for fear of loss of our cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rofit, em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loyment, or this or that mans favour, we shall withhold he confession of the truth, when we are thereunto cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. There is a memorable story, for this purpose, related by <hi>Aeneas
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119464:11"/> Silvius, de gest. Conc. Basilensis l.</hi> 1. when there was a question, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordinary Presbyters were to have a place, seat and vote, in nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and general counsels, as well as Bishops. This same Historian was for the Presbyters, having equal power with the Bishops, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self had formerly seen it at the counsel of Constance; but speaking of the carriage of things in the counsel of <hi>Basil,</hi> he speaks of one <hi>Abbot Panormitan,</hi> who fearing least the simplicity of the Presbyters should overcome the ambition of the Bishops, (being a man of great learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and one that the counsel much looked on) would only have the Bishops have a voyce in Counsels: This Historian (who was a Scribe in this Counsel) complains thus; <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>videtis quam pauci nobiscum sunt &amp;c.</hi> You see how few are with us, and they fear the face of the mighty, and lay a stumbling block in their nimbleness; you have heard to day the voyce of the Prelates; you have heard that they all said, they rested in the will of the King, but none in the will of God: but the Presbyters are they who had righteousness, truth and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, God himself before their eyes, &amp;c. But speaking of this <hi>Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitan,</hi> who would not in this Counsel assert the truth, as it was his duty; he adds, <hi>Panormitanus postquam domum venit in Cubicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum se recepit &amp;c. Panormitan,</hi> after he came home, betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self into his bed-chamber, and complained with himself of his King, that he compel'd him to fight against the truth, and to lose his name and soul, and in the midst of tears he falls asleep; there was only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them one Italian Bishop, and the Abbot of <hi>Doway,</hi> who for their constancy, and most firm will to the good of the whole Church could not be changed from their purpose.</q> This story is cited by <hi>Phil. Morney, Tract. de Eccles. Cap.</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 515, 516.</p>
            <p>A spice of this was in <hi>Peter, Gal.</hi> 2.12. when certain Jews came, who were zealous for Circumcision, and Seperation from all Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Gentiles; <hi>Peter</hi> seperated himself from the Gentiles, though formerly he had kept company with them, and he should have pleaded, that it was lawful to keep company with them as he did, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.5. upon the ground that he saw a vision, that he ought so to do; and upon this ground, that they had received the Holy Ghost, as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll as the Gentiles, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. And he, in not putting forth these princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, as he ought, did in some measure deny Christ in his truth, though not in that measure he had formerly in the high Priests Hall.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Christ is denyed implicitely, which is, when, though we do not deny him in word, or life, or writing, because we are not put to any of these, yet we would deny him were we put thereto; thus millions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119464:11"/> of people deny Christ: were it put upon most men, whether they would confess such a truth as should cost them the loss of a cow, they would not confess it; how much more would they deny a truth that should cost them all their estates, nay lives also. To rectifie the frame and habits of our hearts are those commands of self-denyal. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. &amp; 14.26, 27. The sum whereof is, That every man that would approve himself Christs Disciple, must do or suffer any thing for Christ, must forsake all that he hath when God calls for it, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.33. life and all, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.38. And how the habits must stand in point of confession, Christ shews by two similitudes; one of a house, which he that builds considers what it will cost to build; the other, of a King going forth to battel, who considers whether he be able to meet his Adversary with proportionable resistance: So must every Disciple consider, whether he hath an habit to leave any enjoyment, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo any suffering for Christ and a good conscience; until such time as such an habit is wrought in the soul, though thou dost not expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely or visibly deny Christ, yet thou denyest him implicitely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretively.</p>
            <p>Such an habit <hi>Luther</hi> had before he came to use it. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolarum ad Spalat. pag.</hi> 296 297. he saith thus; <q rend="margQuotes">Thou askest me what I will do if I be called of the Emperor <hi>Charles;</hi> I answer, if I cannot go well I will be carryed sick; I doubt not but I am cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God, if <hi>Caesar</hi> call me; if they go to violence then I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>use to God; the same lives and reigns that preserved the three children in the <hi>Babilonian</hi> furnace; but if he will not preserve me, my life is but a small thing if it be compared to Christ; presume all things of me except flight and recantation. <hi>haec ille.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now forasmuch as if thou hast a disposition in thy heart to deny Christ, though it never come to tryal. God will find it out; therefore I hold it expedient and profitable, if not one man to another yet eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to his own soul, to propound in this manner; Soul, what wilt thou do if altar-worship? Saint-worship, or any other superstition thy soul abhors, comes to be prest on thee, what wilt thou do? Or if it be put to thee to subscribe to doctrines thy heart cannot allow, as, that works justifie in the same kind of cause; That justified persons may and do totally and finally fall away and perish eternally; or any doctrine of the like kind; wilt thou, O my soul, subscribe or suffer the loss of all? If thy heart say such things are false, but yet I must practise them, and subscribe to them, or else I cannot enjoy my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and my inheritance; truly God looks upon thee as one yet in the gall of bitterness and bond of iniquity; and such persons do not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119464:12"/> scape a curse in this life: But if thy heart say as <hi>Raul, Gal.</hi> 6.14. <hi>God forbid that I should rejoyce in any thing, save in the Cross of Christ,</hi> or more then a good conscience; such a testimony will make thee to rejoyce in sickness, and triumph in death. Such things <hi>Justin</hi> Martyr was wont to put to himself <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <q rend="margQuotes"> I therefore expect to be insnared of any one of those that are of any note or name, and to be crucified; or especially of <hi>Crescens</hi> the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher, <hi>Justin. Mar. Apolog.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Rom. Senatum.</hi> This <hi>Crescens</hi> afterwards accusing of him, as appears in his life, was the cause of his Martyrdom; so that according as he expected it came to pass, from this vain glorious and covetous <hi>Crescens.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Ʋse</hi> for tryal, Seeing that habitual denyal excludes out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, try whether you so deny Christs; tryals hereof are these;</p>
            <p n="1">1. When we set limits to our foregoings and sufferings, when per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons will part with so much, but not with all; some will endure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches for Christ, but if they be cast into prison, to get their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they will either deny or recant the truth; others there are that will be content to lose their liberty, but are resolved what ever come they will hold their estates; if it be thus with thee, that thou wilt leave thus much, or venture thus much for Christ, but thou wilt leave no more, truly thou dost habitually deny Christ; for if God shall put thee upon a greater measure of obedience, thou wilt deny Christ whensoever thou shalt be put thereupon. It was a speech of Doctor <hi>Taylor,</hi> in a letter to Doctor <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and others, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess Christ <hi>ad ignem</hi> exclusive, that is, in words and outward profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; but few stick to him <hi>ad ignem</hi> inclusive, that is, in deed and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering 'for his sake.</q>
               <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 677.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, persons that habitually confess Christ, set no bounds to their sufferings or to their forsakings. <hi>Abraham,</hi> when God would have him forgo his Country, he did it; when he bid him cast out <hi>Ishmael,</hi> he did it; to sacrifice <hi>Isaac,</hi> he did it in intention; nay, had God bid him to sacrifice his own life, I doubt not of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness: In like manner, <hi>Moses,</hi> he left the honor of a Court, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to endure reproaches, and appeared before <hi>Pharaoh</hi> divers times, though not without hazard of life. <hi>Paul</hi> was not only ready to be bound, besides whipping, and other perils he endured, but was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ready to be put to death for Christ, <hi>Acts.</hi> 21.13. It is related by <hi>Pamelius</hi> in the life of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> set before his works; <q rend="margQuotes">That in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians</hi> time, there was a certain form of Testimonial or Certificate, which divers persons that would retain Christianity (and yet its to be feared would not suffer death for it) were wont to offer to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consul
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119464:12"/> or Governor, which were called <hi>libelli lapsorum;</hi> the form of it was this, as appears in the Epistle to <hi>Antonianus; ego prius le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geram &amp;c.</hi> I formerly read, and the Bishop handling, knew that the Servant of God ought not to sacrifice to Idols, nor worship Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and therefore, lest I should do that which was not lawful, when the opportunity of a testimonial was offered, (which I would not accept had not an opportunity been shewn;) I came to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, or another by my command, saying, I am a Christian, it is not lawful for me to sacrifice, I cannot come to the altar of the Devil, I give a reward for this thing, that I may not do that which is not lawful for to do.</q> Thus we see some would part with their goods to hold their consciences, that they might not do that which is not lawful for to do: but had there been a Magistrate that would not have received a bribe, its to be feared, they would flatly have abjured and denyed the truth; and so do many in these times, they would let go something for the Lord, but rather then let go all for him, they will deny him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's a sign a person will habitually deny Christ, when a man hath only an outward profession of Christianity, but hath not clear light and folid principles to uphold it; this is like a stately building without a foundation to support it. Men may talk and argue of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in prosperous times, as they please, but when it comes to the point, there is no man will suffer further then he hath clear light to convince him, and solid principles to uphold him in suffering: Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of light made <hi>Shadrach, Meshach</hi> and <hi>Abed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ego</hi> so confident, that when the King threatned a fiery furnace, if <hi>they would not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship the golden Image;</hi> they answered, <hi>O Nebucadnezzar, we are not careful to answer thee in this matter, Dan.</hi> 3.16.17. There is no ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant man, let his profession be what it can be, that doth not habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually deny Christ: <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Hebrews, Heb.</hi> 10.32. after they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, endured a great fight of afflictions, partly, whiles they were made gazing stocks, both by reproaches and afflictions, and partly, whiles they became companions of them that were so used;</q> note, first they were inlightned, and then they endured.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It's a sign a person habitually denies Christ, when his consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence steers by the compass of humane Laws, when he is ready to follow what they set up, without ever looking whether it agree with the word. Most men are like those, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.7. who when the King commanded, that whosoever would not worsh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p the golden image should be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace, <hi>they all f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll down and worshipped the golden image.</hi> What comfort can any man have in his worsh p, when he receives it upon the commands of men?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119464:13"/> He that takes his worship or religion upon the command, authority, or compulsion of this or that man or magistrate, will let it go again upon the command, authority, or compulsion of the same or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man or Magistrate: Yet what is more common in the mouths of multitudes then this saying, what authority sets up I will receive? which is in effect to prostitute our consciences to a creature, and to have Gods fear taught us by the precepts of men, <hi>Isa.</hi> 29.13. Ask multitudes, why they cast off the Mass-Book and received the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book? and why they cast off the Service-Book and received the Directory? Their answer is, not because they thought any of the three agreed with the Scriptures, but because authority imposed it upon them, or injoyned them thereto: So that if the authorities of the world should put down all these three, and set up the <hi>Turkish Alchoran</hi> (it makes my heart to tremble to speak of this Atheistical time-serving) thousands, its to be feared, would receive it. <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> on the fourth command, saith, <hi>Plures sunt Ecebolii;</hi> now this <hi>Ecebolius</hi> was in <hi>Constantines</hi> time a Christian, in <hi>Julians</hi> time a Heathen, and in <hi>Jovinians</hi> time a Christian; as these Emperors changed so did he: A certain Cardinal in <hi>France</hi> said of the English scoffingly, That they beleeved in their King more then in their God. So do too many make the charge appear, that persons beleeve in their Magistrates more then in their God. It was well answered by Mr <hi>Berty</hi> husband to the Lady <hi>Katherine,</hi> Duchess of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> when <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Steven Gardiner,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> askt him whether the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy his wife were as ready to set up the Mass, as she was to pull it down; he answered in these words, As touching setting up of Mass, which she learned not only by strong perswasions of divers excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent learned men, but by universal consent and order, whole six years past, inwardly to abhor, if she should outwardly allow, she should both to Christ shew her self a false Christian, and to her Prince a masking subject: You know, my Lord, one by judgment reformed is more worth then a thousand transformed temporizers: to force a confession of Religion by mouth, contrary to that in the heart, worketh damnation where salvation is pretended; <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 927.</q> And further in the person of the said Duchess, he said 'she was to be turned by perswasion and not by commandment. God is wont to work a religion in religion the hearts of his people before they make profession of it visibly.</p>
            <p>Nay should men or Magistrates bring people to the profession of that which were Gods eternal truth, yea should they dye in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of it in obedience to the Magistrates power, either for fear or love, shall they be saved? No, they shall not, but they only whom the love of God constrains to obedience.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119464:13"/>
            <p>It was the praise of <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> King of <hi>Kent,</hi> of whom the Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian saith, <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. vol.</hi> 1. <hi>page</hi> 150. 7 Edition, <q rend="margQuotes">After the King was thus converted, innumerable others dayly came in, and were adjoyned to the Church of Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st, whom the King did specially embrace, but did comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l none; for so he had learned that the faith and service of Christ ought to be voluntary and not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>These speeches should be as so many beacons upon an hill to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thee that thou steer not thy conscience according to the commands of men; and know certainly if thou goest on so to do, thou hast an habit of denial of Christ in thy heart, which as soon as a tentation cometh, will bring it self into act, and that so often as thou shalt be tempted.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is a sign a person doth habitually deny Christ, when his life is vicious and unholy; acts proceed from habits; and as a thing is in being so it is in working; when mens practises are bad, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Christ in them, all such do much more deny Christ in their dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions of heart; that man who will not leave a lust for Christ, will much less leave an enjoyment: Its much at one to a wicked man in what religion he lives, seeing he is resolved to live loosely: No man denies Christ in an ungodly life but he hath first habitually denyed him in his heart: The mystery of the faith and a pure conscience are both held together, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.9. And when the ship of the soul is cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, they both suffer shipwrack together, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. The consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence being lost in a loose life, as soon as a storm of persecution ariseth, the faith formerly professed is cast away.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is a sign a person doth habitually deny Christ, when he doth ordinarily and usually withhold truth and wink against light; indeed good men may withhold truth too much and not suffer consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to speak out in some cases, as <hi>Asa,</hi> who was a good man, but he imprisoned <hi>Hanani</hi> for telling truth; but when this is ordinary and frequent, then undoubtedly we have an habit of denyal of Christ, <hi>Isai.</hi> 30.10.11. they said (not only to one, and so but once) <hi>to the seers, see not, and to the Prophets, prophesie not;</hi> but to the seers, in the plural number, they spake so often in their gestures and cariage, though not in words; so many in the days when Episcopacy was in the height, were loth to read books against Episcopacy, because they never meant to close with such truths as might be a break-neck to their preferment. Men reason thus, If I shal receive truth and not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise as it shall direct, then will my conscience torment me for sinning against it in the omission of a duty; and if I do practise, according as truth and conscience shall direct, then shall I expose me and mine to persecution: Hence men do with truth, as <hi>Herod</hi> did with the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119464:14"/> who imprisoned him first, and then kil'd him after; or as Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velers, who fearing those they meet on the high way will rob them, ride at as great a distance from them as they can. Persons fearing that truth will rob them of such an enjoyment, and expose them to such a suffering, lose them friends, and procure them enemies; hence they are, as <hi>Peter</hi> expresses it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5. willingly ignorant; or as the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist hath it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.15. they have closed up their eyes, lest they should see with their eyes; they wink at truth for the present, and have an implicite intention to deny it hereafter. Hence <hi>Amaziah</hi> could not endure <hi>Amos</hi> to preach at the Kings Chappel, and the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision-Teachers <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.12. could not endure <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting Circumcision; not that they thought Circumcision ought to be practised, but meerly for fear, lest they sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld suffer persecution. The more open the heart is to receive truth, especially in times when the owning thereof shall expose to great hazards or sufferings, the stronger usually is the habit and disposition of soul in confessing thereof. The soul is in a right frame, when it can say, Speak Lord, for thy servant heareth, I am ready, with <hi>Cornelius,</hi> to hear all things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to me from God.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A wordly frame of heart is a sign a person doth habitually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Christ, when the heart clings close to house, land, trade, wealth, or earthly enjoyments, that in the frame of his heart he resolves not to leave them. Hence <hi>Demas</hi> left <hi>Paul,</hi> and left Christ in leaving him; the cause was, he loved this present world. That Scribe that seemed to be so forward, that he would follow Christ whithersoever he went, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.19. When Christ told him, <hi>the foxes have holes, and the birds of the ayr have nests, but the son of man hath not where to lay his head;</hi> we read not that he went any further with Christ, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. The yong man did deny Christ in a request or command; which was, that he should give all that he had to the poor; what was the cause? why, he had great possessions, and a heart glued to them, for he was sorrowful it went to his heart to leave them, <hi>ver.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>Many do with the Lord, as <hi>Orpah</hi> did with <hi>Naomi,</hi> who went with her a while; <hi>Orpah</hi> as well as <hi>Ruth</hi> said, <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.10. <hi>Surely we will return with thee unto thy peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> but when <hi>Naomi</hi> propounded worldly respects, <hi>Orpah</hi> kisses her mother, and weeps, <hi>ver.</hi> 14, but <hi>Ruth</hi> clave to <hi>Naomi, ver.</hi> 14.16. saying thus to her, <hi>Intreat me not to leave thee, or to return from following after thee; For whether thou goest, I will go, and where thou lodgest, I will lodg; thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God, where thou dyest I will dye, and there will I be buried, the Lord do so to me, and more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, if ought but death part thee and me:</hi> So many worldly men, as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119464:14"/> well as godly seem to go along in confession of Christ; but when they see the confessing of such truths, and the owning of such ways, will cost them the loss of their trades or estates, they sorrowfully take their leaves of Christ, and his Truth, being sorry they cannot grasp both: but he, who in the habit of his heart confesses Christ and his Truth, saith, I will not return from following Christ, nor from own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his truth; God forbid that either trade, wealth or life it self should take me off from Christ or his truth. <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his book, <hi>de lapsis, p.</hi> 240. speaking of some Christians that sacrificed at the Devils altars, and renounced Christ, and having told them that they needed not bring any other sacrifice, for he that came to these altars to sacrifice was himself a sacrifice; there, saith he, thou hast sacrificed thy salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thy hope, thy faith hast thou burnt in those deadly fires; neither, saith he, was there any just cause which could excuse such a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness; thy Country was to be left, and thy Patrimony was to be lost: And thou he adds, Brethren, the truth is not to be dissembled, nor the matter and cause of our wound to be kept silent; the blind love of Patrimony hath deceived many, nor can they be ready to go away whom their estates like fetters have bound; these were the bonds and chains wherewith vertue was kept back, faith pres'd, and the soul shut up.</q> So that we see what was the matter and cause of this wound of denying Christ, even an eager love of this world, and if we doubt that this is one cause of this wound, the Apostle will put it out of question, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10. who saith, some coveting after money have erred from the faith or as <hi>Cyprian</hi> reads it, <hi>Naufragaverunt a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> they have made shipwrack of their faith by denying the same, and pierced themselvs through with many sorrows of an accusing <hi>cōscience</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Ignorance of the worth of Christ is another sign that the soul doth habitually deny Christ; till a man be convinced, that the having Christ is a greater good then all other goods, and the loss of him a greater evill then all other evils, let a mans profession be what it will, he doth habitually deny Christ; the Merchant will not part with a pound, much less with a 1000 pound for a jewel, till he know the worth of it; but when he knows the jewel is ten times the worth of his estate, oh, saith he, let all my estate go, so I may but gain it; so when the soul knows and beleeves the excellency of Christ, oh, saith he, let all go for him; yea, he counts it none of the least causes of his rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that he had something of worth to part with for Christ.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Ʋse.</hi> If Christ wil deny those that habitually deny him, it may be a caution to us, that we deny not Christ in the habits of our heart. We read in the Counsel of <hi>Nice,</hi> the eleventh Canon, that those that trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressed by denying Christ in one act they were enjoyned divers years
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119464:15"/> pennance;<note place="margin">Cyp. de laps. p <hi>24<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> the words of the Counsel are, <q rend="margQuotes">Of those, who besides neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity have transgrest (by necessity, I suppose, he means extremity of tortures, as <hi>Castus</hi> and <hi>Aemilius,</hi> who in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time, in the first encounter were overcome, but in the second were Conquerors) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther because of the taking away of their goods, or because of danger, or such like, which was done under the Tyranny of <hi>Licinius.</hi> It plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses the Synod,<note place="margin">Vide Can. <hi>4.</hi> post. Cap <hi>3</hi> cum Ringer. Annot.</note> that if any repent from the heart, they be three years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the hearers, and seven years <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be among the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and two years without oblation (by which he means the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, wherein they were wont to offer bread and wine for the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as well as for the poor, and other uses;) they shall partake with the people in prayer:</q>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For they kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling some upon the slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der against us, drew the inhabitants of our houses to torments, as children or wife, and by horrible tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments do necessitate them to spe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k those things which are fabled &amp; falsly reported of them. <hi>Justin. Mar. Apol.</hi> 1 <hi>p.</hi> 39. He means, they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de them confess that Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans fed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pon mans flesh, or, as I suppose, eate their ch ldren, for in the same page he mentions the former.</note> If the denying Christ in one act be so dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, what is it to do it every hour, as those do, who deny Christ ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually. There is a threefold denyal of Christ.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sudden, when a man is taken on a sudden, as <hi>Peter</hi> was; to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this, consider aforehand thou mayst be taken on a sudden with some great tentation; it may be, some desperate fellow may threaten to kill thee if thou wilt not renounce thy faith; it may be, a company of persons may compass thee about, and threaten to kill thee, if thou wilt not sign, or vote that which thou knowest to be unjust. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Christians must do as Marriners, who foreseeing a storm may come on a sudden, make all their cords and tacklings firm during the calm; resolve aforehand, in Gods strength, rather to dye, then do a thing thou knowest to be unjust, and so deny the Lord that bought thee, for want whereof many weak ones miscarryed in <hi>Justines</hi> time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a deliberate denyal of Christ; the more reluctations, checks, and deliberations a person hath for the confessing of some truth of God, and yet hangs back and denies it, the greater is the sin; though this sining willingly after we have received the knowledg of the truth be not the sin against the Holy Ghost, for which there remaineth no more sacrifice for sin, being it is done out of fear rather then malice, yet may it be some step to it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26. So fearful were some Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, in the primitive Church, of this deliberate denying of Christ, <q rend="margQuotes">That when some out of pity would have had the Christians seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as if they sacrificed among a great company that did sacrifice, and they would have cryed out, that they had satisfied the Kings Commandment; these Christians would not thus deny Christ, but some of them cryed out that they had not sacrificed but were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians; others with greater faith cryed out, that they never had sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, neither would.</q>
               <hi>Eu tropius lib. r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, Rom. c.</hi> 11. Though this deliberat denyal of Christ be very dangerous, yet I doubt not but some have fallen into it, and repented thereof, and after deliberately have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Christ and his Truth.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119464:15"/>3. But specially take heed of habituall deniall of Christ; for, 1. If thou deniest Christ habitually, thou setst up some other God in thy soule, to whom thou adherest more then unto Christ, that is our God for whom we leave all other things: famous was the carriage of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leddo,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Fox, Acts &amp; Mon. p.</hi> 305. out of <hi>Basilius Magnus,</hi> (others call her <hi>Juletta</hi>) this widdow had great Lands and many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <q rend="margQuotes">who being oppressed by a Cormorant that dwelt close by her, so that she was constrained to goe to Law with him, the Judge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding of this Tyrant why he wrongfully with-held these Lands, the Tyrant answered, that he might so doe; for this woman is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to the Kings proceedings, for she will in no wise worship his gods, nor offer sacrifice to them: then the Judge hearing that, said unto her, Woman if this be true, then thou art not only like to lose thy land, but also thy life, unlesse that thou worship our gods, and doe sacrifice unto them; to whom <hi>Juleddo</hi> answered, Is there no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but either to worship your false Gods, or else to lose my lands and life? then farewell sute, farewell lands, farewell children, yea and farewell life too, and in respect of the honour of the everliving God, farewell all: and with that saying did the Judge commit her to Prison, and she suffered most cruell death.</q> Certainly, no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies Christ habitually, but he hath set up some other god in his heart, either of profit, or of credit, or earthly greatnesse.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If thou thus deniest Christ, thou deniest thy best friend, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest him become thy worst enemie; how friendly was Christ to <hi>Judas</hi> before he denied him? he let him beare the bag, but after he had deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, how did he for that and his treason fill his soule with horror? we are loth to deny a deare friend in any reasonable request, let us not deny Christ in his reasonable requests, we had our estates and lives from him, let him have them againe if he call for them, learne of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9.6. <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to doe?</hi> wilt thou have me to leave of my Iudisme? I am content: wilt thou have me to go to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son? I am content; yea not only to bonds, but to death, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. Christians must take heed of denying their best friend Jesus Christ, least as he fills the Spirits of them who confesse him with invisible comfort by his Spirit, so by the same Spirit he fills your soules for deniall of him with invisible horrour, that your life shall be a kind of Hell, and none can take off that wrath that he sets on upon the soule. It was a good exhortation the Lady <hi>Jane Gray</hi> gave to her sister the Lady <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> in a letter to her, <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. p.</hi> 35. saying, <q rend="margQuotes">I exhort you that you never swerve from the Christian Faith, neither for hope of life, or feare of death, for if you will deny his truth to lengthen your life, God will deny you and yet shorten your daies; and if you cleave
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119464:16"/> to him, he will prolong your daies, to your comfort and to his glory.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Whosoever habitually denies Christ, is as an Apostate from God: Let a mans profession be never so great, and his esteeme among men never so high, yet is he a backslider in heart, and so must look to be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the fruit of his own waies, <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.14. whence came <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Coppersmith so to slide back, when as some think he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly witnessed Christ to some hazard, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.33. the cause was he had denied Christ in the habit of his heart. <hi>Cyprian de lapsis p.</hi> 239. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines that many that thus habitually denied Christ, did apostatize, <q rend="margQuotes">his words are thus: presently at the first words of the threatning enemie the greatest number of the Brethren betraied their Faith, nor were they cast downe with violence of persecution, but they cast downe themselves with a voluntary fall, —he adds, they did not wait, that being askt they might deny, that being apprehended they might set on fire Frankincense: before the battell many were overcome, and without encountring throwne down: neither did they leave this to themselves that they might seeme unwilling to sacrifice unto the Idols, they ran willingly to the Court, they hasted willingly unto death, as if this were the thing they desired, as if they would embrace an occasion given which they had alwaies wisht.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 Whatsoever things we shall save by deniall of Christ, we shall be sure to lose them; and what things we shall lose by confessing Christ, we shall be sure to save them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.39. he that findeth his life shall lose it, and he that loseth his life for my sake, the same shall find it: the meaning is, carnall men think, Oh I have saved my estate, liberty and life by denying Christ, and complying to errour, but such and such have lost all: but Christ tels thee otherwise, that which thou hast saved so unworthily, thou hast lost it, and thy soule to boot; and that which the other hath lost in confession of Christ, he hath saved it for ever: cast up this gettings now, thou hast saved thy estate, and wounded thy conscience, saved thy Body, and lost thy Soule, this is to save the ship and lose the lading, save the Cabinet and lose the Jewels: <hi>Judas</hi> denied Christ and got 30 peeces of Silver, but did not he vomit it up? <hi>Joseph</hi> contrary lost his credit, by going to <hi>Pilate</hi> to beg Christ his Body, as being supposed to be a criminous person, but ever since his name hath been as a sweet ointment powred out: Hence <hi>Luther</hi> Tom. 4.35. B. spake so boldly saying thus, <q rend="margQuotes">We will suffer our goods to be taken from us, our name, life, and all we have, but we will not suffer the Gospell, Christ or Faith to be taken from us; here every man must be most stiffe, unlesse he meane to deny Christ, here I car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the title <hi>Cedo nulli,</hi> I give place to none, &amp; from my heart rejoyce to be called rebellious and stubborne.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119464:16"/>3. Use. Exhortation to confesse Christ in the habit of thy heart: as he denies those that deny him, so will he confesse those who confesse him: we think it a great credit when we are in company, that a Prince or Noble-man should single us out, and take us by the hand, and call us by name, and courteously salute us: Oh! how much more honour and happinesse will it be for Christ to owne us at that day of Judgement, saying, these were they that did not deny my Name, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13. see how Christ speakes to the Angell of Pergamus, <q rend="margQuotes">I know thy works, and where thou dwellest, even where Satans Seat is, and thou holdest fast my Name, and hast not denied my faith, even in those dayes wherein <hi>Antipas</hi> was my faithfull Martyr, who was slain among you where Satan dwelleth;</q> Christ did not onely take notice of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, but of the dangerous times wherein the Confession was made: when we confesse him in the midst of dangers and enemies, Christ will say, these confest my Name, though hereby they suffered spoiling of goods, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.34. these confest me to the losse of their Countrey, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9. <hi>John</hi> was banished to the Isle of Patmos for the Word of God, and testimony of Jesus Christ; 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 11.16. such as set their hearts to seek the Lord God of Israel, left their possessions, and came to Jerusalem, hereby making confession of true Worship against <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi> corruptions, these have borne witnesse of me to the losse of their lives, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11. those that overcame the great red Dragon and his Agents, <hi>overcame him by the blood of the Lamb, and the word of their testimonie,</hi> and loved not their lives to death: had the Saints in the first 300. yeares been silent and contented themselves in a bosome faith, the red Dragon or the Devill in the ten first Persecutions might have long agoe swallowed up Christianity; abundance of soules go to hell in a fancied faith, thinking it enough to salvation to believe that there was such a person as Jesus Christ crucified at Jerusalem, who rose againe, and in the mean time they have no intention to confesse him with the losse of any thing, and yet in Gods sight no lesse mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of confession will serve, then to confesse him in the habit of our hearts, with the losse of our lives; how farre are these from Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, notwithstanding this fancy faith?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rules in Confession are these.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It must be seasonable, it is a Rule in Divinity, the necessity of a meane is judged in relation to the end; suppose a mad-man or drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard should hold forth a sword, and proffer to kill him that should confesse himselfe to be a Christian, here we are not to confesse, because neither glory to God, nor edification to our brother comes hereby; but when the glory of God and edification of our brethren shall be promoted hereby, then we are bound to confesse: see the practice here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119464:17"/> in Christ, when there were many false accusations brought against him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.62. <q rend="margQuotes">he answered nothing but held his peace, but when <hi>v.</hi> 63. the high Priest adjures him by the living God that he would tell whether he were the Christ, the Son of God or not, though the profession of this truth was joyned with manifest hazard of his life,</q> yet because it tended to the glory of God, and edification of his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, he boldly profest it, and answered, v. 64. Thou hast said, that is, thou hast said what I am; and <hi>Mark</hi> sets forth cap. 14.62. more plainely, that Christ to this question answered, I am.</p>
               <p>Many by confessing unseasonably of a truth not necessary, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie themselves and others; some weake Christians hereby expose themselves, and which is more, the cause of God to laughter, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the hatred of the world, and some of Gods people to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution, <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.44, 45. Christ having healed a Leper, bad him say nothing of it to any man but to the Priest, but he blaz'd the matter so, that Christ could no more teach in the City, but was faine to go into desert places. A truth seasonably confest doth not by the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship it exposes the Confessor to, hinder, but rather further the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Gods people, see it in <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 1.12, 13. the Philippians no doubt supposed that <hi>Pauls</hi> imprisonment would have dishartned many, and so hindered the course of the Gospell, but <hi>Paul</hi> tells them othervvise, v. 12. <q rend="margQuotes">but I would you should understand brethren, that the things which happened unto me, have fallen out rather unto the furtherance of the Gospell,</q> and he shewed how the Gospell hereby came to be furthered: First, my bonds for Christ are manifest in all the Palace, even in the Emperours Palace, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.22. for there were Saints in <hi>Caesars</hi> houshold, next v. 14. <q rend="margQuotes">many of the brethren in the Lord (who no doubt were formerly fearfull) waxing confident by my bonds, are much more bold to speak the Word of God without feare.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Onely this I add, though the confession of Christ be not alwayes and every where necessary and seasonable, yet must we have alwaies an inward disposition to confesse Christ and his cause, with the losse of all that we have, but where or how farre this habituall disposition is to produce it selfe into act, where, when, how oft, after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and how farre, it is hard to set a precise rule, but the generall rules of Gods glory, the edification of our brethren, the urgency of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, the voice of the Spirit, with an enlightned understanding, will much direct herein.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our confession must be couragious, not faint-hearted: <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> feared not a whole Councell, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. when the Councell had straitly commanded them that they should not teach in the name of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119464:17"/> Christ, yet they preached, and accused the Councell for slaying of the Sonne of God, v. 30. How bold was <hi>Ioseph, Mar.</hi> 15.33. the Text sayes, <q rend="margQuotes">he went boldly and begged the body of <hi>Iesus,</hi> which was a cleere witnessing of Christ. <hi>Paul</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.) though all men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooke him at his first appearance before <hi>Nero,</hi> yet he stood to it, and God stood to him.</q>
                  <hi>Shadrach, Meshak</hi> and <hi>Abednego, Dan.</hi> 3.17. were not fearfull, but valiant in confessing the true God, against <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzars</hi> image set up in the plaine of Dura, notwithstanding threats of a fiery furnace. Reason, either the cause is Gods, or it is not: if it be not, why do we move in it? if it be, let us resist unto blood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.4. Famous was <hi>Luthers</hi> courage herein, saith he, <q rend="margQuotes">That I may not speak boastingly, I stood at Lypsidge, disputing before a most dangerous company; I appeared at Augusta before most wicked enemies, though I had not obtained Letters promised for my security: I came to Wormes into the assembly of <hi>Caesar</hi> and all the Nobility of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, though I knew before the publike promise to be broken, and divers snares to be laid for me, yet had I then such a courage, that if I knew there were as many <hi>malos Genios,</hi> or Devills to shoot darts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me as there were tiles in the houses in Wormes, yet had I come thither, <hi>Ad Freder. Elector. &amp; frratrem Iohan. p.</hi> 226. <hi>b. Cyprian Epist.</hi> 57. praises the Brethren for the confession of Christ unto banishment: they stood armed to the battell; he saith, they could not be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come but they could die; and in this they were unconquered, that they feared not to die. Such a couragious answer was there in <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nysius</hi> and <hi>Faustus,</hi> and their companions, when the Governour <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milianus</hi> had called them into the Councell, he spoke to them after this manner, <hi>viz.</hi> We have put the power of your own lives into your hands, if ye will turn your selves to that which is according to nature, and worship our gods, and altogether forget those gods which are against nature: <hi>Dionysius</hi> answered, You doe not all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship the same gods, but every one have gods according to their will, but we worship one God, the Maker of all things: the Governour askes againe what hinders, why you may not worship this God (if he be God) with other gods, to which <hi>Dionysius</hi> answered, we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship no other God but one, whereupon the Governour banished these servants of God into the parts of Lybia upon paine of death if they went not, <hi>Euseb. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Courage is one principall property in a Souldier, we professe our selves Souldiers to fight under Christ his Banner, therefore for the confession of his Name we must not feare Devills, Prisons, Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Burnings, Hangings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. feare none of these things which thou shalt suffer, the Devill shall cast some of you into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119464:18"/> what is all our profession if we have not an intention couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to confesse Christ even unto death?</q>
               </p>
               <p>That thou mayest be couragious in confession, consider but these things, that though Satan endeavours to scare thee from duty, with proposing the sweetnesse of liberty, yet remember, that when they imprison thy body, they set thy soule free. Besides as with <hi>Ioseph,</hi> so with thee God will go into prison, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.21. God can turne the Jai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors heart to be mercifull to thee, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.33. but if not, imprisonment cannot sever from: Christ; is not the prison of hell and of a bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science the worst of prisons? <hi>Nec hoc vos consternet, &amp;c.</hi> let not this cast you downe, that you are severed from the world, for if we would consider, that the world is rather a prison, we shall understand, that you are rather gone out of prison then into it, <hi>Tertul. lib. ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. cap.</hi> 2. a little after he saith, the world hath greater darknesse, which blinds the minds of men, heavier chaines which bind the soules of men, breaths out worse filthinesse then lusts of men, containes more guilty persons, to wit all mankind, then the prison doth: It's no difference where ye are in the world, who are without it, <hi>Ibid.</hi> Also <hi>cap.</hi> 3. doth not the spirit get more in the prison then the flesh loses? yea the flesh doth not lose the things which are just, which are supplied by the care of the Church, and by the love-feast of the Brethren.</p>
               <p>But if only there be but a noise of dying for Christ and his Truth, Oh! how are persons startled! yet why shouldest thou be thus startled? thou makest an Idoll of thy life, if thou wilt not let it go when God calls for it, thy life of it selfe will depart from thee: how canst thou then better part with it then for God? die thou must, when, where, and how, thou canst not tell, other men part with their lives of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, do thou part with it as a Sacrifice: besides, is not all that thou hast at Gods Command? If he will call thee out of thy Countrey, thou must goe, though thou knowest not whither, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.8. if out of the world, thou must go, yea, and that way he will have thee, whether by burning, drowning. Besides is not the death of the Saints, though oft reproachfull, with men, yet precious in his sight, <hi>Psal.</hi> 116.15. and to conclude if thou beest faithfull in confession to death, thou shalt have a Crowne of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. Imagine it were said to a man, that after he had suffered an houre of torment, he should have the happinesse of a Kingdome for an hundred yeares, what would he not suffer? if thou indurest death for confession of Christ, here's an eternall Crowne, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.12. Shall hope of victory and praise make a Souldier stand in the midst of guns and bullets, and shall not the crowne move us to stand? Shall Princes have their Martyrs, and States their Martyrs, and the Pope have his Martyrs, and Christ have none? what man goes to build an house, and considers not what it may cost?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119464:18"/>3. The third property in confession is, that it must be plain,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. But that we may not lie nor deceive those that exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine us, glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confessing Christ, we die, when we could do according to the saying, I swore with my tongue, but my heart swore not. Iustin. Matt. Apol. 2. p. 61.</note> &amp; not equivocall; I speak not of Logicall Equivocation, which is when a word hath two or more plaine significations, and the persecutor deceives himselfe, but of Jesuiticall Equivocation, which is when a man expresses one part of a proposition, and reserves another part in his mind; as if one should ask a Jesuit, whether he were a Priest, and he shall answer no, reserving this in his mind, he is no Priest of <hi>Jupiter:</hi> in confession of Christ, we must abandon such deceit, for even such deceit may befall men in Christ, as appeares <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Peter</hi> when the Circumcision faction came to Antioch, he dissembled both his Doctrine and practise of eating with the Gentiles, which before and after he practised: if we be called before Councells, and Governours, let us answer in plain English, remember we have to deale with the searcher of hearts. <q rend="margQuotes">When one <hi>Dionysius</hi> was commanded by the Governour <hi>Aemilianus</hi> that he should cease from profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing himselfe to be a Christian, thinking that if he changed his Faith, others would change with him, <hi>Dionysius</hi> answered plainly, we ought to obey God rather then man, and openly professed that he worshipped him who is God alone, and no other; neither would he change his Judgement, nor at any time cease to be a Christian, <hi>Euseb. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 10. When <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were asked this question by the Councell' <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.7. by what power or what name they had healed the lame man,</q> they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered plainly, v. 10. <hi>Be it knowne unto you by the name of Jesus Christ, whom yee crucified, doth this man stand before you whole.</hi> Contrarily we see in this case, how the Parents of the blind man dissembled, the Pharises <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.19. asked how her sonne came to see, they answered v. 21. they knew not by what meanes he came to see; they knew well enough how he recovered his si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht, but they durst not declare it; the reason is rendred v. 22. because they feared the Jewes, who agreed that if any man would confesse him, he should be put out of the Synagogue, but the blind man their son plainely confesses v. 30. 33. that Christ was of God, whereupon he was cast out of the Synagogue: what is and hath been more common in this age, then for men if brought before higher powers, to flam over things with a lie, or cheat, or trecherous subscription, either to what the higher powers or inferiour Courts required, so cunning and carefull is the flesh to save it selfe with the losse of conscience: where is the spirit of <hi>David?</hi> I will speak of thy testimonies before Kings and not be ashamed <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.46.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119464:19"/>
               <p>Famous was the plainnnesse of <hi>Cyprian</hi> herein, as it is set downe by <hi>Reinerus Bachofius Eehtius</hi> in his life, <hi>pag.</hi> 685. which he cites from <hi>Pontius Cyprian</hi> his Deacon, who writ his life and suffering. <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Galerius Maximus</hi> the Governour having sent for him, when he came to him he asked him, art thou <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Cyprianus? Cyprian</hi> answered, I am. <hi>Galerius</hi> the <hi>Proconsul</hi> said, art thou he whom the Christians call their father? <hi>Cyprian</hi> answered I am; the <hi>Proconsul</hi> said, our Princes have comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee to worship the gods, <hi>Cyprian</hi> answered, I will not do it, the <hi>Proconsul</hi> repli'd, thou wouldst do better if thou woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st provide for thy safety and not contemne the gods; <hi>Cyprian</hi> answered, Christ is my safety and power, whom I desire to serve for ever; the <hi>Proconsul</hi> said, I am sorry for thy life and would provide for thee; <hi>Cyprian</hi> replied, I desire no better thing provided for me then that worshipping my God, I may hasten to him with all earnestnesse of mind, because the suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this life are not worthy of the glory that shall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in us: <hi>Galerius</hi> the <hi>Proconsul</hi> being angry, said, thou hast a long time lived with a wicked mind, and hast gathered men of a wicked conspiracy unto thee, and hast showne thy selfe an enemie to the gods, and therefore thou shalt be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to others, and in thy blood they shall learn instruction; then he gave sentence saying, let <hi>Statius Cyprianus</hi> refusing to sacrifice to the gods be beheaded, which sentence being after recited out of a table, was excecuted. We see in this worthy Saint, what a Chrstian plainnesse was manifested.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Eusebius lib.</hi> 8. cap. 3. sets forth the manner of those who strove in persecution under the Emperour <hi>Dioclesian,</hi> saying, one being brought to those wicked sacrifices, though he did not sacrifice, yet seeming as if he had sacrificed, he was sent freely away; another though he had not come neer (meaning to the altar) nor touched any impure thing, yet the Gentiles saying that he sacrificed, being silent he bore their reproach, and so broke away; Another cried out with a loud voice, that he did altogether refuse their sacrifices; another rejoycing in the wholsome name of Christ, cried out that he was a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; another affirmed for certaine, that he neither had sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, neither would sacrifice hereafter: if the like times of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all should come, there would be, as plainnesse in some in their confession, so much deceit in others.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119464:19"/>4 Let this confession be with meekenesse and feare, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Be ready to give an answer to every one that asketh you a reason of the hope that is in you, with meeknesse and feare:</hi> Meekenesse to men, to all men, to the Persecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ors, whether Magistrates, or others; a proud passionate cariage in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any truth never gained any persecutor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the faith, but many have been wrought upon by an humble meeke cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; let there be also feare, both feare of God, that what we professe with our tongue, the searcher of hearts may testifie with us, and feare of men, having a respective humble cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age towards them. See this meeke cariage in Christ his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.22. when a Souldier smote him with the palme of his hand while he was speaking, see how meekely Christ speaks, <hi>vers.</hi> 23. <hi>If I have spoken evill, beare witnesse of the evill; but if well, why smitest thou me.</hi> A proud tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous boysterous cariage, hinders the passage of the most glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous truth, though confest with much plainenesse: let there be meekenesse in opposition to pride and fury, meeknesse in opposition to revenge, after Christs example, <hi>when he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted hee threatned not,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.23.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Let thy confession be with constancy, let times be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable or adverse, yet still confesse the same truth. <q rend="margQuotes">It was the brand of the stony ground hearers, that as soone as tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation or persecution did arise because of the word, <hi>by and by they were offended, Mat.</hi> 13.21. <hi>Cyprian de lapsis, pag.</hi> 238 speaking of the Saints of those times saith. The beautifull troupe of the Souldiers of Christ is prese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, who by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant encounter have broken the turbulent cruelty of the pressing persecution, being prepared to the suffering of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment, and armed to the enduring of death.</q> Such a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposition was in <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 21 13. <hi>I am content not onely to be bound, but to dye for name of the Lord Iesus.</hi> Moreover <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> addes, <hi>Pag.</hi> 241. <q rend="margQuotes">He may complaine of torments, who is overcome by torments; he may pretend excuse of griefe, who is overcome in griefe; such an one may intreat and say, I would truely strive valiently, and bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g mindfull of my Sacramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all bond, I tooke up the weap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns of devotion and faith, but divers torments and long punishments overcome me, fighting in the encounter, but my mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de stood fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119464:20"/> my faith strong.</q> Such were those Worthies, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.35. others were tortured not accepting deliverance that they might obtain a better resurrection; the meaning is, when they were upon the racks, the persecutors offered them deliverance if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y would recant such a truth as they had begun to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, or if they would subscribe to such a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> errour as they had began to protest against; but these Saints, though they felt the vehemency of their anguishes, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sible of the benefit of present ease, yet would they not com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> off from their tortures. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at death, torment, and torture, ought we not to endure ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n sin deliberately against our consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, in not co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fessi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g constanel; fie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces, and Lyons denns o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght not to be sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d in this case; we cannot alledge a nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssity of sinning, when our religion calls for a nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssity of not sinning. If we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne deliberatly against our conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lesse per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aps in ease of extreame tortures, may we not qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r there be any uprightnesse in us. If this bee not the pitch of Gospel-obedience not to sinne against consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for the escaping of cross<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, or the ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aining of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I know not what is; If at every great lift, we may sin against our consciences to esape some great crosse, or obtaine som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great enjoyment, sure then it is nothing to be a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; and the commands of Christ of leav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng all for him, seeme to be to no great purpose: Gods trayning up of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> first to leave his Countrey, and then to sacrifice his son; his directing of <hi>Moses,</hi> first to leave the pleasures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and then to suffer reproches and other afflictions with Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his inuring of <hi>Paul</hi> to be in deaths often, in stripes, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse and hunger, doe poi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t out to us, that we ought to do duty, of which confession is one of the principall, whatsoever become of us. It was well said of a moderne learned man. <q rend="margQuotes">As he is not to be counted an Orthodox Professor that holds his Creed when none gainesayes, but doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, or recants, when the adversary opposes; so is he no Christian, but tainted with hypocrisie, that assents unto the goodnesse of divine precepts, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>les tentations are farre off, but dis-esteeme therein the choise, whiles they come in competition with sensuall pleasures, to which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le adde, or sensible tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119464:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iackson</hi> on the Attributes, <hi>pag.</hi> 74. but being he explaines this more fully, <hi>pag,</hi> 80. <hi>Ibid.</hi> Ile recite his words, saith he. <q rend="margQuotes">Wee are then said to beleeve matters of our owne salvation, when we assent unto them as good, as necessary, and worthy to be embraced, not onely while considered in themselves or in generall, or without such encumbrances as doe oftentimes terpose or hinder their practise; but even whilst they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually compared with present losse of any sensuall good, or infliction of any transitory evill, which the world, the devil, or the flesh, can oppose to raise their price.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The point whereupon our Confession revolues, as the doore upon the hinges, or the Heavens upon the Pole, is this, that God upon no termes is to be left, but that the enjoyment of him is a greater good then all other goods, and the losse of him a greater evill then all other losses. I am the larger in in this property, not onely beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se there are many divine truths in our first apprehension <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssented unto as good, and therefore truely willed, whiles simply considered, which wee evidently refuse or nill, when we come to question about their price; but also because in peaceable times there are many principles which we embrace as absolute truths, which when we are called to suffer for, we first beginne to question, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be truths, and afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a small consultment with flesh and blood, we conclude the Negative, that such things so for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly acknowledged for reall truths, are now no other then falsehoods and mistakes; and if the times whirle about again, persons they can re-assume their former principles but yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day condemned, and they shall be absolute truths tomorrow, which is in effect to play fast and loose with the searcher of hearts.</p>
               <p>Most certainely perswaded even the weakest must and ought alwayes to be, upon the highest termes of absolute necessity, to confesse the eternall truth of God, and not to be daunted for the opposition of man or devill, which how this can be in any uniformity in religion (unlesse the agreement be in very gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls) without the persecution of many such weake ones, seemes to me to be a mistery.</p>
               <p>Onely we must distinguish betwixt Articles of our Faith and opinions; the former we must constantly so confesse, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119464:21"/> we dare venture all we have in this present world upon them, the latter which is opinions or probabilities of which there are many deduced from Scripture, these we confesse sufficiently when being asked, we confesse our selves to hold such a thing as an opinion; but our judgement doth rather incline to this side, or the other, but yet not without some feare of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>It was well said of one, <hi>Burrowes</hi> heart divis. p. 176. <hi>ex Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> whose words are. <q rend="margQuotes">If I did not find in my selfe a love and desire of all profitable truth; if I did not put away idlenesse, and prejudice, and worldly affections, and so examine to the bottom, all my opinions of divine matters, being prepared in mind to follow God, and God of only, which way soever he shall leade me; if I did not hope that I either do, or endeavour to do these things; certainly I should have littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hope of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining salvation: to which I shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dde, whatsoever truth God shall lead me unto, in such a mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> flight, that I shall acknowledge it to be undoubtedly on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gods truthes.</q> If I have not an habit in my heart, to confesse it to the losse of limbe, liberty, and life, I can have no ground to believe, that either my faith, is a faith unto righteousnesse, or my hope, is a hope unto glory, seeing the Apostl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> saith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. with the heart, man believeth unto righteousnesse, and with the tongue, Confession is made unto Salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Motives to Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssion of Christ and his Truth.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis habituall Confession is the most evident tryall of our faith, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 4.13. <q rend="margQuotes">we believed, and therefore have w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> spoken, ye b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and therefore speak;</q> the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list, Iohn</hi> 12.35 proves th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unsoundnesse of the rulers, because though they believed on Christ, that is with a notionall assent, that he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore then a man; yet because they did no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lieve on him savingly, that is, they did not adhere and leaue upon him, as their Saviour better then life, and all the enjoyments of it, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither did they tast of the sweet comforts of his spirit in their s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ule; hence they not believing thus (though they did giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an assent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Doctrine that he taught) they would not conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse him, least they should be cast out of the <hi>Synagogue, Rom.</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119464:21"/> 10.10. with the heart man believeth unto righteousnesse, and with the tongue Confession is made unto Salvation; as if he should say, Confession is an inseparable concomitant of faith, there is no man whose heart believes unto righteousnesse; but the same mans tongue is ready to confesse the truth he doth believe.</p>
               <p>By which tryall of confession, the unsoundnesse of the faith of thousands is discovered, who take and leave their Religion upon the streame of times, or commands of men, and are ready either to have a Confession regulated by the commands of men, or else lye hid in a bosome-faith without any kind of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and to use <hi>Zwinglius</hi> his words, as they are cited by a learned man, <hi>Epist.</hi> 3. <q rend="margQuotes">we may as well with <hi>Dioclesian</hi> worship before the Altar of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> as conceale our faith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power <hi>Antichrist,</hi> no man that dyes a Christian, dyes with a politick bosome-faith, but with a disposition to confesse Christ and his truth.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The absolute necessity of Confession to Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. with the tongue Confession is made unto salvation; which is not meant of Confession in the eare of a Priest, as if that were necessary to Salvation; but of Confession of truth in the habit of the heart brought forth into a Confession in words; many things a person may be ignorant of, and live and dye in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of through ignorance, and yet obtain Salvation; but without this Confession, there is no Salvation, as Christ is the cause of reigning, so is Confession a requisite, withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which we do not reign, <hi>Luke</hi> 14 33. <q rend="margQuotes">whosoever he be among you, that forsaketh not all that he hath, he cannot be my Disciple, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. others were tortured, not accepting deliverance that they might obtain a better resurrection:</q> they knew that Confession of Christ, and a better Resurrection go hand in hand to Confessours, Salvation is promised, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32. <hi>he that confesses me before men,</hi> that is, such men as shall oppose my truth, or shall sollicit you to deny it, or shall threaten you with losse of imployment, liberty, or life, if you go on in the Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of such and such principles, I will confesse every such man before my Father in Heaven; but if on the other side, for feare of the losse of goods, liberty, or Countrey, he shall no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> confesse my truth, he must never looke for salvation; but must expect as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119464:22"/> deepe a place in torments, as unbelievers, nay as murderers, wh remongers, sorc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rers, and Idolaters, see <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8. but the fearfull and murderers, &amp;c. shall have their part in the lake, which burneth with fire and brimstone. But on the other side, he who overcom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that, overcomes all threates of men, by a constant co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fessi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, the sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e shall be clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hed in white Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 3 5. after the manner of the Princes and Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the earth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9 8. Let they Garments be alwayes white, see <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> 9.3. Christ in his transfiguration had Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments exceeding white as snow, so as no Fuller on earth can white them, and the Angel that appeared at the Resurrection, his Rayment was white as snow, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.3. the meaning is, those that confesse Christ, shall be cloathed with the same kind of glory, that the Angels of Heaven are invested withall, yea, that Christ himselfe hath, differing only in degrees, yea, Christ saith further, I will not blot out his name out of the book of life, that is, I will declare him to be written in the book of my election: so was <hi>Clemens, Phil.</hi> 4.3. there is a writing in Gods booke of election, according to appearance of men, these may be blotted out, see <hi>Psal.</hi> 69.28. <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.8.17.8.20.15. &amp; there is a writing according to truth; thus victorious Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours are writ in that book, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20. these cannot, shall not be blotted out, and though <hi>Moses</hi> desired it, rather then <hi>Israel</hi> perish, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. yet was it only his abundant love to God, and his brethren that made him desire impossible things; nay, this is not all, but Christ addes, I will confesse him before my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and his only Angels, that is. Christ will avouch these are they that overcome the Dragon by the word of their Testimony, and loved not their lives unto the death, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The assistance we shall have from Heaven in this duty, should move us to it, if in any duty we can expect assistance from Heaven, then in this duty of confession, which so nearly concernes Gods glory: if any man doubt of assistance herein, see Gods promise for it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.19.20. <q rend="margQuotes">when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you up, meaning to Councels and Governours, as v. 17. 18 take no thought how or what you shall speak, for it shall be given you in that same howre what ye shall speak; for it is not ye that speak, but the spirit of your Father, which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119464:22"/> speaketh in you, when you come with an honest heart,</q> resolving to speak what you believe, Christ will assist you what to say and you shall so speak to purpose, that all your adversaries shall not be able to gainsay, nor resist your wisdom, as <hi>Luke</hi> sets it down, Cap. 21.15. and how was this verified in the confession that <hi>Stephen</hi> made in <hi>Acts</hi> 6.10. <hi>those that opposed</hi> him, were not 'able to resist the wisdom &amp; the spirit, by which <hi>he speake;</hi> what assistance had <hi>Paul</hi> when he was brought before <hi>Caesar</hi> to confesse the name of Christ, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. when all men forsooke him, God stood by him, the words are at my first Apologie, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> no man stood with me, but all men forsooke me, let it no be acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed unto them; but the Lord stood by me, and strengthened me, when he was but in his journey t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wards his Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssion, see how G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d appeares to him, <hi>Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 27.24. feare not <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ou sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought before <hi>Caesar,</hi> how did God as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urs &amp; Martyrs in their sufferings; <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Rose Allen</hi> when persecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing <hi>Tirrel,</hi> askt if she would burne for company sake, sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> answered not for company sake, but for Christs sake, then <hi>Tirrel</hi> tooke a Candle-light and held her hand over it, it burning so long, that the very sinewes brake in sunder, being asked how she could endure the painful burning of her hand, she said at first, it was some griefe to her; but afterwards, the longer she burnt, the lesse paine she felt, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi> p. 830. the like is related of <hi>Cuthbert Simson,</hi> who was thrice in one day rackt in the Tower, the first time, three howres in a rack of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, p. 865. because he would not discover who they were, whom he did well to come to their worship, this man when he lay in prison, had a vision of exceeding comfort, one came in to him in prison at eleven of the Clock, opening 3. doores, and having no Candle nor Torch that he could see, but giving a brightnesse and light most comfortable to his heart, said, Ha, unto him, and departed againe, p. 866. this story <hi>Cuthbert Symson</hi> told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o one Mr. <hi>Austen</hi> 4. times.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And as God assisted them in their sufferings, in making them to endure tortures: so did he assist them in their answers, to the shame of persecutors, I will instance but in one to avoide tediousnesse, (though upon search I could instance in many) wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch was one Priests wise, who could not so much as reade, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi> p. 889.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119464:23"/>
                  <speaker>'Bishop.</speaker>
                  <p>Art thou a mans wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I have an Husband and Children, and have them not; so long as I was at liberty, I refused neither Husband nor Children; but now standing here as I do stand in the Cause of Christ and his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ruth, where I must either forsake Christ or my husband, I am contented to stick only to Christ, my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Spouse, and ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unce the other: he that leaveth not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, sister, brother, husband, is not worthy of me.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Christ spoke this of the Martyrs which dyed, because they would not do sacrifice to the false Gods.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">And I will rather dye then worship that Idoll, which with your Master you make a God.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">You callet, will you say, the Sacrament of the Altar is an Idoll.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">There was never such an Idoll, as that which Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>sts command to be worshipped with fond fancy; but Christ commanded to be eaten and drunken in remembrance of him.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>Did not Christ say this is my Body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Yea, but he meant not carnally, but sacramentally▪ for which I will give my reason.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure it will be goodly geere.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>Such as I will lose this poore life of mine for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>Then you will be a Martyr.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">If the denying to worship that breaden God, be my Martyrdom I will be a Martyr; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> for my reason, this it is, Christ doth sit at the right hand of God: therefore he is not in a peece of bread; if he did offer his body once for all, why do you make a new offering.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">You are a jolly Protestant, in what Schooles have you been brought up.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I have upon the Sund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ies visited the Sermons, and there have I learned such things as are so fixed in my breast, that death shall not seperate them.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">But if thou wert an honest woman, thou wouldest not have left thy Husband and Children, and run about the Countrey.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Sir, I laboured for my living, and as my Master
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119464:23"/> Christ counselleth me when I was persecuted in one City, I fled to another.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>who persecuted thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">My Husband and children, for that I would have them to leave Idolatry, and worship God in Heaven, I fled, because I would not be partaker in that foule Idoll the Masse.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Let this mad-woman be put down to prison, till we send for her husband.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I have but one husband, who is here already, and in prison with me, then sundry Priests talked with her.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priests.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Leave of thy wicked opinion about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Altar, the naturall body and blood of Christ.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Be ashamed to say a peece of bread is turned into the body of Christ; which bread doth mold, and mice eat, Gods own body will not be so handled, and kept in prison and boxes, let it be your God, it shall not be mine; for my Saviour sitteth on the right hand of God.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Priests.</speaker>
                  <p>Now truly the Divell hath deceived thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">No, God hath opened mine eyes to see the right use, and your abuse of the blessed Sacrament.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Old Fryer.</speaker>
                  <p>What sayest thou of the holy Pope?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">He is Antichrist, and the Devill, then they all laughed.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Nay, you had more neede to weepe, then to laugh, and to be sorry that ever you were borne to be Chaplains of that whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> I defie him and all his falshood, get you away from me.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Priests.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, we come for the profit of thy soule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">How save you soules, seeing you preach damnable lyes, and destroy soules?</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Priests.</speaker>
                  <p>How provest thou that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">You damn soules, in that you teach people to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship the worke of mens hands, and to worship a false God of your own making of a peece of bread, and that there is a purgatory, when Gods sonne hath by his passion purged all, &amp; you make God, &amp; sacrifice him, when Christ his body was a sacrifice once for all; you teach people to number sins in your eares, &amp; say they be damned, if they confes not all, when
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119464:24"/> Gods word saith, who can number his sins; you sell your prayers for money, and make them b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y pardons.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">This godly woman having a moneths liberty, coming into <hi>Peters</hi> Church, beheld there a <hi>Dutchman</hi> making new noses to Images that were defaced in King <hi>Edwards</hi> time.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">What a mad man art thou to make them new noses, which in a few dayes shall all lose their heads.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Dutchman.</speaker>
                  <p>He accused her, and called her whore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Thou art accursed, and so are thy Images, thy Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are whores, and thou art a whore-hunter; for doth not God say, you go a whoring after strange Gods: then was she clapt up, and had no more liberty.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Gentlem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of the Countrey.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Leave thy fond opinions, thou are not able to answer such high matters.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I am not, yet with my death I am content to be a witnesse of Christ his death, my heart is fixed, I will never turne to their superstitions.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>'Bish.</speaker>
                  <p>The D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vell leades her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">No, it is the spirit of God, who leadeth me, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me in my bed, and at mid-night, and opened his truth to me.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priests.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">After the sentence was read against her, the <hi>Priests</hi> told her, her life should be spared if she would recant.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, God forbid that I should lose an eternall life for this carnall and short life, I will never turne from any heavenly husband, to my earthly husband; from the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of Angels, to mortall Children: and if my Husband and Children be faithfull, then am I theirs: God is my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God is my Mother, God is my Sister, my Brother, my Kinsman, God is my Friend most faithfull.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>Thus you see the great assistance this poore woman had from God in her answers, though she could neither write nor read, whose answers I have briefly set down, though at large they are more fully exprest. <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi> p. 889. 890. 891. by which we may gather what assistance the weakest confessor of Christs truth m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y expect.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Motive. Habituall confession is an evidence of our union with God and Christ. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.15. <hi>Whosoever shall confesse that Iesus is the sonne of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God:</hi> this
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119464:24"/> confession is not meant simply to confesse this proposition, [Jesus is the Sonne of God] in word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly; for so all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>England, Scotland, France, Spaine,</hi> &amp;c. confesse, and the carnallest amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g them, would be ready to fly in the faces of those that sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uld gainsay it, nay, this the Divels confes, <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.24. <hi>I know thee who thou art, the holy one of God,</hi> to understand therefore what this confession was, know that it was as much as a mans reputation was worth to confes Christ to be the Son of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.22. the Jews agreed, that if any man did confes that he was Christ, he should be put out of the Synagogue; nay, it was a ma ter of imprisonment: <hi>Sauls</hi> Commission was, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.2. <hi>That if he found any of that way, whether men or women he should bring them bound to Ierusalem:</hi> and <hi>verse</hi> 14. <hi>Ananias</hi> saith, he had authority from the chiefe Priests, to bind all that call on thy name: Yea, for confessing of Christ in Preaching, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were whipt, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.40. and <hi>Paul</hi> five times, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 25. Yea, for the confession of Christ, <hi>Peter</hi> was put to death, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 21.17. and <hi>Iames, Act.</hi> 12.2. So it was a matter often ignominious, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Capitall to confesse Christ: So the meaning is, that whosoever in times and places shall confesse any fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall point or cause, when its accompanied with hazzards, as that truth then was, and the same truth in some places of the world at this day is, it is a declarative evidence of his union with the Lord. That an habituall confession of Christ with the losse of all, is an evidence of the spirit being in us, see 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10.11. <hi>Alwaies bearing about in the body the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord Iesus, that the life also of Iesus might bee made manifest in our body; for we which live are alwaies delivered unto death for Iesus sake, that the life also of Iesus might bee made manifest in our mortall flesh.</hi> The meaning is this, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it was objected to <hi>Paul</hi> and other Christians, that they were in continuall danger of death, the Apostle answers, what then? First, it is the dying of the Lord Jesus, both because it resembles Christ suffering and dying for us, and also because it is for his sake. Secondly, it is a manifestation (whiles we have such an habit to confesse Christ, that the life of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus is in us, and then <hi>vers.</hi> 11. the Apostle shewes that this was a finall cause why he and other Saints had an habituall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119464:25"/> intention to dye for Jesus sake, and therein to confesse the truth of God, for of that he speakes, <hi>vers.</hi> 13. we having the same spirit of Faith, as it is written. <hi>J beleeved, and therefore have I spoken:</hi> we also beleeve, and therefore speake.) Which finall cause was, that the life of Jesus may be manifested in our mortall flesh, that whiles wee are ready to lay downe our mortall lives for Christ, we may manifest both to our selves, and others, that the life of Christ is in us. So that as God said to <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he was ready to but the knife to <hi>Isacks</hi> throat, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12. Now know I that thou fearest God, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou hast not withheld thy Sonne, thy onely Sonne from me; so will Conscience say unto thee, now know I, that thou hast a spirituall life in thee, and art united to Christ, seeing thou dost not withold any of thy dearest comforts from the Lord, but art willing to leave them all, for the confession of him, and his truth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Motive to stir us up to confession, is the abundant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort God is wont to give his people in their confession. When <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> had confessed Christ before the Counsell, <hi>they went away rejoycing, Act.</hi> 5.41. When the Jewes stirred up the devout and honourable Women, and the chiefe men of the City, and raised persecution against <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and no doubt, against others of the brethren with them, and expelled them out of their coasts, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.50. its said, <hi>The Disciples were filled with joy, vers.</hi> 52. <hi>Act.</hi> 23. <hi>When Paul had witnessed the truths before the Counsell,</hi> among other truths the truth of the Resurrection, <hi>and upon a dissention that arose betwixt the Pharisees and the Sadduces was in danger of being pulld in peeces, ver.</hi> 10. That very night the Lord stood by him, and said, <hi>Be of good cheere Paul, for as thou hast testfied of me at Jerusalem, so must thou also beare witnesse of me at Rome, vers.</hi> 11. when <hi>John</hi> was banished into the Isle of <hi>Patmos,</hi> for the word of God, and testimony of Jesus Christ, <hi>he was in the spirit on the Lords day, and received those giorious reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Revel.</hi> 1.9.10. To him that overcomes, not onely some particular lusts, which naturall men may doe being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by rationall principles, but all lusts, and more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, those lusts which are wont to assault us with treachery, to Gods truth, <hi>Hee that overcomes,</hi> I <hi>will give him the hidden
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119464:25"/> Manna, Revel.</hi> 3.17. that is, the comforts of the Spirit, which taste as sweet to the conscience, as Manna to the taste, <hi>and</hi> I <hi>will give him the white stone,</hi> that is, the sentence of absolution in his owne conscience, alluding to the manner of absolutions in old time, which were writ in white stones by the Judges, as sentences of condemnation were in blacke. So that as God is wont to instill comfort into the soule when it melts in Confessions and humiliations, or when it hath been conslicting with some strong lust, and hath got vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, or when the soule puts forth, its strength in duty, and wrastling prevailes with God, as <hi>Iacob, Hos.</hi> 12.3. who by his strength had power with God, he wept and made suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and found the Lord in <hi>Bethel;</hi> so is the Lord wont to drop in comfort, when wee confesse his name to the losse of some deare enjoyment, the want whereof is made up with inward comfort, proportionable to the measure of what we foregoe for God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. Else how could we receive an hundred fold, brethren, and sisters, and father, and mother, and children, and lands, with persecutions, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.29.30. and that not onely in heaven, but also <hi>in this time,</hi> in the Greeke, <hi>now in this time,</hi> and that when we are in close pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and want every one of these; so that we receive so much comforts from the spirit of God, as equals, nay, farre exceeds the comforts that all these could give unto us if we had them together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philpot</hi> the Martyr said, as I remember, in a Letter to the Lady <hi>Vane,</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Beleeve it there is no such joy as that the Saints feele under the Crosse, when they imprison our bodies they set our soules free. Master <hi>Bradford</hi> also in a Letter to his Mother, <hi>Acts and Mon. Ʋol.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 308. saith, 'Indeed I thanke him more of this prison, then or any parlour, yea, then of any pleasure that ever I had, for in it I finde God my most sweet God alwaies. <hi>Luther</hi> said of one <hi>Taulerus,</hi> that man of God, (as he calls him) upon his owne experience said, That God is never more kind and amiable unto his children, never more sweet and familiar then after the triall of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</q> But we need not goe to particulars, seeing all Saints, but specially those that have suffered for a good conscience, finde it an experimentall truth.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119464:26"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vocati sumus ad nulit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m, &amp;c.</hi> VVe are called to the war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are of the living God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n th n when we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>svvered to the vvords of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Tertul ad Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yrs. cap.</hi> 4. VVh t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ese words are he tels us in his booke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aptisme</note>6. The sixeth motive to confession of Christ, is our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, its the Apostles owne motive, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>Having washed our bodies in pure water, let us hold fast the conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssion of the hope, without wavering;</hi> as if hee should say, Baptisme bindes Christians to an unwavering confession. To be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d into the name, doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; profession of Christ, and in our hearts to denie his truth, what is it save a meere mockery: the dispensatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Baptisme is upon a presupposall that we are Christs Disciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. Make disciples all nations, <hi>bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them;</hi> but how are we Christ his disciples, if we have not learned to deny al (friend, and life, and all) for the Lord? <hi>Lu.</hi> 14.26, 27. which sure we have not done, if we have not learned ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually to confess<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord. To be Baptized into the faith of Christ, and after to deny Christ, is, as if a Soldier listed under the command of his Captaine, or Colonell, should renounce him and sight under the enemies banner. Without beleeving, <hi>Philip</hi> told the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> it was not lawfull to be baptized, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37. Now all true faith which is unto righteousnesse, hath a confession also unto salvation conjoyned with it. When a tentation comes to deny the Lord, or be ashamed of his cause, let us repell it thus; am I not baptized into the doctrine of Christ, and shall I deny the Faith of Christ, am I not a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of Christ? and therefore not be cowardly, nor a runne-away from my Colours when the battell is to be fought.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The seventh motive to confession of Christ, is the horror of conscience that have befallen them that have denyed Christ, and his truth, besides Christ his denyall of them in heaven, Christ is wont to fill their consciences with horror, feare: witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse <hi>Judas,</hi> who having in heart denyed his Master, (which <hi>Peter</hi> never did) went out and hanged himselfe. <q rend="margQuotes">Famous is the story of <hi>Jacobus Latomus</hi> of the University of <hi>Lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> who in his publike Lecture fell in an open fury and madnesse, uttering such words of blasphemeus impiety and desperati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, that the other Divines which were there, namely, <hi>Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rdus, Athusianus,</hi> were faine to carry him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as he was raving, and so shut him into a close Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: from that time unto his last breath.<hi>Latomus</hi> had never any thing else in his mouth, but that he was damned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected of God, and that there was no hope of salvation for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119464:26"/> him, because that wittingly, and against his knowledge, hee withstood the manifest truth of his word, <hi>Acts and Mon. Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 964. <hi>ex epist. Senarcles ante hist. de morte Deazij.</hi>
                  </q> But some may object, this denyall was of the highest nature, it was the sinne against the Holy Ghost, <q rend="margQuotes">therefore no wonder it was punished with such horror; therefore see what horrour came upon Judge <hi>Hales,</hi> being overcome, as was supposed, by the fraudulent assaults of Doctor <hi>Day,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> and Judge <hi>Portman,</hi> he was brought in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o great terrour of conscience, and thought himselfe utterly forsaken for his denya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l of Christ; so sending downe his servant for a cup of beere, (having lyen all the night sobbing and groaning) in the morning wounded himselfe with his Penknife, in divers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his body, but his servant returning, he was stopt of his purpose that time, but in a short while after going into the Country, and having set all things in order, he drowned himselfe.</q>
                  <hi>Acts and Mon. Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 186. But some may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, perhaps this man was a wicked man, and therefore God filled him with such horror for denying the truth.</p>
               <p>See then the example of ago lly man whose soule was filled with horrour, for denying Christ, it was <hi>Thomas Bilney</hi> of of whom <hi>Latimer</hi> in his seventh Sermon saith, <q rend="margQuotes">I knew a man my selfe, little <hi>Bilney,</hi> that blessed martyr of God, who what time he had borne his faggot, and was come againe to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> had such confl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cts within himselfe, that his friends were afraid to let him be alone; they were faine to bee with him day and night, and comfort him as they could, but no comforts would serve; and as for the comfortable places of Scripture, to bring them to him, it was as though a man should have runne him through the heart with a sword. Also in his eight Sermon, <hi>fol.</hi> 132. he saith, When <hi>Bilney</hi> came to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> after the bearing of his Fagot, a whole yeare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was in such anguish and agony, that nothing did him good, neither eating nor drinking, nor any other communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Gods Word; for he thought all the Scriptures were against him, and sounded to his condemnation. <hi>Latimer</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten communed with him, but all things whatsoever any man could alledge to his comfort, seemed to him to make against him, yet for all that, afterward he came again: God endued
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119464:27"/> him with such strength of faith, that he not only confessed his saith in the Gospel of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sus Christ; but also suffered his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be burned for the same Hipocrisie, and that volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily; for taking leave of his friends in <hi>Trinity</hi> Hall, telling them he would go up to <hi>Ierusalem</hi> (alluding to <hi>Paul:</hi> Speech) he went into <hi>Norfolke,</hi> and there preac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed privately, to confirme the Saints, then preached he openly in the fields, confessing his fact, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d preached publikely the Doctrine which before he had abjured, untill his apprehention, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. Vol.</hi> 2. learne we then from these examples, not to deny the truth, least God fill us with like horrour.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. The eight Motive. The examples of Saints who have confessed Christ before men, examples either of good or evill, are apt to set us on fire. Christ, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.13. being brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> witnessed a good confession, and it was at such a time, when his life was in hazard by confessing, and a likelihood of safety by denying from this High-Priests confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: the Apostle exhorts the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to confesse, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.1. compared with <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.14. the <hi>Hebrews</hi> seeing many sufferings to attend the confession of Christ, for feare thereof they were ready to startle aside: here the Apostle bids them consider the High-Priest of their confession: the word in all places is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which signifies confession, he confessed the truth here, and is now entered into Heaven, to interceede for us, and to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist us by his power in confession; therefore let us hold fast the disposition of confessing his name: see <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. <hi>When all men forsooke him, he confest Christ and his truth. Peter</hi> did the like before a Counsell, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.46. <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.18 <hi>Bee it known unto thee ô King, we will not serve thy Gods, nor worship thy golden Image:</hi> the flesh indeed hath a principle never to venture further in confession, then one may be free from danger, and not to put any further to Sea, then they can safely put in againe into the Haven, if they see a storme com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; and they think persons mad that will expose themselves to danger by confession; but a Christian is never in a right frame, till he seeme to the world to be mad.</p>
               <p>We are not to follow the patterns of carnall men, those that looke to be excellent in any art or science, choose out the rarest patterns, so must we; would we be eminent in Christianity, we
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119464:27"/> must not propose unto our selves some coward that runs away before the battle, but behold those that loved not their lives in the cause of God, in comparison of the holding of the word of their testimony, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.11.</p>
               <p>Such an one was <hi>Iohn Badby,</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">who being condemned for his confessing the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, was brought into <hi>Smithfield</hi> to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, when the Prior of Saint <hi>Bartholomew</hi> brought the Host and shewed it to the Martyr at the stake: they demanded of him how he believed in it, he answered, he knew well it was hallowed bread, and not Gods body, and then was the Tun put over him, and fire put unto him, and when he felt the fire, he cryed, <hi>mercy,</hi> (calling belike upon the Lord) and so the Prince immediately commanded to take away the Tun, and quench the fire: the Prince (his commandement being done) asked him if he would forsake heresie, to take himselfe to the faith of holy Church, which thing if he would do, he should have goods enough, promising unto him also a yearly stipend out of the Kings treasury; but this valiant Martyr neglected and refused the Princes proffers; wherefore the Prince com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him straight to be put into the Tun again, and that he should nor afterwards looke for any favour; but as he was not allured by their rewards, so he was not abashed by their torments, but remained invincible till death, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. vol.</hi> 1. pag. 682. See other examples more ancient, there is a memorable example of some such in <hi>Iustine Martyrs</hi> time, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and there was a certaine woman that lived with her husband, an uncleane person, she being also given to uncleannesse formerly, but after that she knew the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Christ, she became continent and wise, and perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her husband in like manner so to be, shewing him again and again the Doctrines of Christ, setting before him that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting fire which is prepared for unchast and voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons that live not continently, and according to right reason; but he remaining in his unnaturall uncleannesses, made his wife estranged unto him by his actions; for she counting it wicked to lye with him, contrary to the Law of nature, and contrary to right, every way to make passages of pleasure, she consulted to be seperated from her bond of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, but her friends disswaded her giving her hope, that her
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119464:28"/> Husband would be changed in time to come, so she continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed still with him; but her Husband after going into <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> was reported to have become much worse, the woman fearing that if hence forward she used the same bed and board, she should be partaker of his wickednesse, giving him a bill of divorce, was seperate from him: upon this, her Husband accused her to the Emperour, that she was a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, the woman being cited, petitioned that she might have leave to set her house in order, and then she would answer the accusation, which when she had obtained, her husband withdrew his bill, and prosecuted against h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r no further (the cause of it <hi>Iustin</hi> doth not expresse; but I suppose, it was least his wife should have accused him of that we call <hi>Sodomy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Emperour) but set upon <hi>Ptolomy</hi> her friend, who had taught her Christian Religion, and got him put in bonds by the meanes of a certain Centurion, he bidding the Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion aske <hi>Ptelomy</hi> whether he were a Christian; for this wicked man knew his uprightnesse, that he would presently confesse what he was, the said <hi>Ptolomy</hi> being long tortured by the Centurion, was in the end brought to the Governour <hi>Vrbicius,</hi> who being examined, confessed himselfe a Christian; for which profession <hi>Vrbicius</hi> commanded him to be carried away; upon this, one <hi>Lucius</hi> a Christian being present, spake to this effect: this man convicted to have committed any wickednesse, art thou moved to punish him, because he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the name of Christian, who is neither Adulterer, Manslayer, nor Robber, O <hi>Vrbicius</hi> thou dost not judge as becomes a godly Governour, <hi>Vrbicius</hi> made no other answer to <hi>Lucius,</hi> but that he seemed to be such an one as one as <hi>Ptolomy</hi> was, and so commanded <hi>Lucius</hi> to be carried away also, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> gave him thankes in that he was freed from evill Lords, and sent to a good God, with these also there was a third, who suffered with <hi>Lucius</hi> and <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> this cruelty of <hi>Vrbicius</hi> the Governour being done in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> and other cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties against Christians else-where, gave occasion to <hi>Iustin Martyr</hi> to write his former Apologie to the Roman Sena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, in the behalfe of Christians, <hi>Justin. Apol.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Rom. Senat.</hi> To these might be added the examples of many others, who
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119464:28"/> are and ought to be unto us parents of confession of Christ, but these shall suffice.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. The ninth motive to sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us up to confesse Christ, is that he will in this case confesse us before his Father in heaven, and so crowne us with glory, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.32. as its true, <hi>that if we deny him, he will deny us;</hi> so is it true, <hi>if wee will confesse him, he will confesse us. Tertul.</hi> in his Book written to the Martyrs in prison (for so, all that then witnessed Christ were called, and the word Martyr signifies a witnesse, <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">These Martyrs in prison vvere vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llent Exhortation, <hi>Timebit forsitan caro, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Perhaps the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h will f are the heavie sword, the high crosse, the sury of beasts, the most exquisite punishment of fire, and all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the hangman in his torments, but let the spirit oppose unto it selfe and the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh, that though these things be bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter, yet are they received of many with a patient minde; yea, willingly desired for fame and glory sake, not onely of men, but also of women, that you also the blessed women may also answer to your Sex.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Lucretia</hi> being ravished,<note place="margin">Deus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalis habeti de cui &amp; Empedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles arden tem frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Aet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit Quas ma aut Horat.</note> slew her selfe in the sight of her friends, that she might glory in her chastity. <hi>Mutius</hi> burn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his hand upon the Altar, (he meanes <hi>Mutius Scaevola</hi>) that same might carry abroad his action. <hi>Heraclitus</hi> who burnt himselfe being daubd over with Cow-dung; also <hi>Empedocles</hi> who leapt into the fire of Mount <hi>Aetna,</hi> and <hi>Peregrinus</hi> who burnt himselfe, out of vaine-glory, when a great part of <hi>Greece</hi> were present at the <hi>Olympian</hi> Games, (as <hi>Pamelius</hi> out of <hi>Lucan,</hi> and <hi>Marcellinus</hi> observes.) Women also have despised the fire: <hi>Dido</hi> when after the death of her most deare husband, she was caused to marry (to one <hi>Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas,</hi> as <hi>Pamelius</hi> expounds it) slew her selfe. The wife of <hi>Asdrubal</hi> when <hi>Carthage</hi> was on fire, seeing her husband Petition <hi>Scipio,</hi> threw her self with her children into the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the City. <hi>Regulus</hi> a Roman Captaine being taken prisoner by the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> being unwilling that he alone should be chang'd for many prisoners of <hi>Carthage,</hi> was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling rather to be given to the enemies, being put into a tub which was every where driven thorow with nailes, hee felt so many crosses. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> poysoned her selfe with Serpents
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119464:29"/> that shee might not fall into the hands of her enemy; if so much of the strength of the body and mind be sold for earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory, that persons despise the sword, fire, crosse, beasts, torments for the reward of mans praise? I can say, these things that you suffer, are but small in comparison of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly glory, and divine reward; if glasse be worth so much, how much is the true margarite worth? Who would not bestow as much upon that which is true, as they doe upon that which is counterfeit.</q> And a little after he addes, these Examples not without cause the Lord hath brought into the World; now to exhort us, and in that day to confound us, if we feare to suffer for his truth to salvation, which others have affected for vanity to destruction.</p>
               <p>And he addes in the 6. Chapter of the same Booke, <q rend="margQuotes">Some man will suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r that for the cause of man, which he doubts to suffer for the cause of God. Herein the present times can teach us, how many persons of quallity put an end to their birthrights, dignities, and lives, for the cause of man, either of him, if they shall doe any thing against him, or of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries if they shall stand for him:</q> alluding to the killing of those who stood contrary to the side of the Emperour <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus.</hi> Shall hope of earthly glory or preferrement make men so to confesse in such dangerous cases, wherein oft they lose themselves and theirs; and shall not the hope of heavens glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie set an edge upon their Confessions? Shall the short glory of a corruptible Crowne make men to goe encounter in the middst of swords and bullets, that they may bee praysed, or have some small reward if they scape alive out of the battle; and shall not Christians who are more then <hi>Conquerors, Rom.</hi> 8.37. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in that they are sure to have a Crowne before they strike a stroke, venture to combat against all oppositions whatsoever, and to confesse the cause of Christ against all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions whatsoever, even to the losse of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But the feare of death is not so much as the feare of torments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> Herein we have the promise, that God will not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer us to be tempted above that we are able, he will either abate the force of the fire, or give us strength to beare it, the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119464:29"/> remainder of wrath God will restrain, <hi>Psal.</hi> 76.10. <hi>Residium iratum cinget, Vatab.</hi> Let the fury of the persecutor goe out so farre as our strength reaches, and girds in the rest; besides <hi>greater is he that is in us, then he that is in the world,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh</hi> 4.4. Was not Christ thy head tortured for thee, when his hands and feet were nailed to the Crosse, remember the tortures of a guilty Conscience for the present, and the tortures of hell hereafter, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. others were tortured, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the word signifies to beat a Timbrell, they were beaten as if they were Timbrels or Drums; <hi>Suidas</hi> uses the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, when men are beat with clubs, or such like instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, so was <hi>Eleazer,</hi> 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 6. and the 7. Brethren, because they would not eat Swines flesh, 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 7. The sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are dreamed no other then humane stories, yet not to bee slighted. <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Eliazer</hi> a principall Scribe aged 90. yeares, being constrained to open his mouth to take in Swines fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh (which was contrary to the Law of God) spit it out, and came of his owne accord to the torment, <hi>vers.</hi> 19. Some of his old acquaintance that had the charge of that wicked Feast, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sought him to bring flesh, such as was lawfull for him to use, and to make a show as if he did eate of the flesh taken from the Sacrifice commanded by the King, that in so doing, hee might be delivered from death, to which he answered, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. It becommeth not my age to diss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mble, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>by many young persons might thinke that <hi>Eliazer</hi> 90. yeares old, was gone to a strange religion, and so through mine hypocrisie should be deceived by me, therefore rather then he would doe this, he chose torment, and was put to death with stripes, 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 7.1. A mother with her seven sonnes were compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the King to taste Swines flesh, who refusing, were tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with scourges and whips, one had his tongue cut out, and was fried in a pan alive, another had the skin of his head with the haire pulld off, and all of them were in the sight of their mother exceedingly tortured, comforting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in the resurrection &amp; life everlasting, &amp; other Scripture consolation.</q> Where extreame tortures are inflicted upon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, their proportionable consolations are wont to abound, 3 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells of the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119464:30"/> have a solemnity among them; wherein certain Noble young youths are whipt before the Altar, their parents and friends standing by, and exhorting them that they persevere, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it a greater glory and side that the life yeelded to the strokes then the body,</q>
                  <hi>Lib. ad Martyr. cap.</hi> 4. Shall persons for glory and fame endure tortures, and shall not we for a good conscience: Besides, if thou beest never so dismembred for a good Conscience, remember thy body shall be raised up a glorious body; it doth not stand with justice, that our b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dy shall be racked and tortured for Christ, and another new made body to weare the Crown.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The tenth motive to confession, is the goodnesse of the cause we confesse, it s the word of God and Testimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.9. the name of Christ, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41. Conscience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. this is thank worthy of a man, for Conscience towards God to endure griefe: this is that which we confesse, and persecuters oppose, Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi> in a letter to the City of <hi>London</hi> saith, <q rend="margQuotes">although my manifold sins have justly deserved all the tyranny that Man or Devill can do to me, yet the Bishops and Prelates do not persecute them in me, but Christ himselfe, his word his truth, and Religion, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi> pag. 310. and in a letter to <hi>Cheshire</hi> and <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kashire,</hi> he saith, the Condemnation, is not a Condemnation of <hi>Bradford</hi> simply, but rather a Condemnation of Christ and of his truth,</q>
                  <hi>Bradford</hi> is nothing else but an instrument in whom Christ and his Doctrine is condemned, how many men have lost their lives to free the Common-wealths of the world from slavery; shall common liberty be a cause worth so many mens lives? and shall our estates, honours, and lives, be too good for the cause of God and Conscience, it was the cause and not the sufferings, only the primitive Christians glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.36. <hi>for thy sake we are killed all the day long</hi> (meaning in the disposition and purpose of their hearts, and in respect of their continuall danger) and counted as sheepe for the slaughter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertull.</hi> in his booke to <hi>Scapula,</hi> that persecuting Governour brings in the Christians glorying in the cause they confessed, Cap. 4. <hi>pro tanta innocentia,</hi> &amp;c. <q rend="margQuotes">we are burned for such inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, for such honesty, for righteousnesse, for chastity, for
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119464:30"/> faith, for truth, for the living God, which neither sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons, nor enemies of the common-wealth, nor trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are wont to suffer; for now this name is vexed of the President of <hi>Legio</hi> and <hi>Mauritania,</hi> even unto death, as it was commanded from the beginning against these, but the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the sufferings, the greater the rewards that follow, your crueltie is our glory.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> on the 69. <hi>Psalme, vers.</hi> 5. hath an excellent histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it was of one <hi>Vsthaz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> Eunuch of the King of <hi>Persia,</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">som times his Schoolemaster, and afterward his faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, who when by the command of the King he was to be put to death for the confession of the doctrine of Christ, he desired this onely, for many benefits bestowed upon the Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and for his continuall faithfulnesse towards the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that he might not be reported to suffer punishment as an unfaithfull person, or as one that deserved ill of the Kings familly, and that it might be signified to all by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Proclamation, that <hi>Vsthazan</hi> was pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to death for no other cause, but because he having embraced the Doctrine of Christ, would not worship the Sun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, nor give divine worship unto it,</q> which when he had obtained, he dyed with a most peaceable spirit. The story is in <hi>Eus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bius,</hi> if my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory saile not, the cause of Christ calls for Confession, and so much the more in that it lies at stake in the midst of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, this advantage we have above glorified Saints, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse Christ in the midst of his friends, but Saints in this life, confesse in the midst of his enemies. Besides, we might have lost our estates and lives for other causes; hence <hi>Bradford</hi> said, <q rend="margQuotes">Oh what benefit? That I who deserved death by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of my sinnes, should be delivered to a conformation and testification of Gods truth.</q> Letter to the U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rsity of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, Acts and Mon. pag.</hi> 331. <q rend="margQuotes">Christians in their Confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions so prized the cause of Christ, that when <hi>Arrius Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in <hi>Asia</hi> did vehemently persecute, all the Christians of that City joyning hands offered themselves before his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment seate, he taking a few of them,</q> said to the rest, <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. O wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ye desire to dye, you have ropes, or places to cast your se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves downe headlong. <hi>Tertul. ad Scap. cap.</hi> 5. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reupon this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119464:31"/> speakes to <hi>Scapula,</hi> the Governour, if it should be done thus at <hi>Carthage,</hi> what wilst thou doe with so many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of men and women offering themselves to thee, how many fires and swords wilt thou have need of, the tenth man in <hi>Carthage</hi> is to be taken of thee, — spare thy selfe, if not us; spare <hi>Carthage</hi> if not thy selfe.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Vse</hi> For exhortation, if Christ will deny those that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitually deny him, be exhorted to learne to deny your selves in the frame-bent, or habit of your hearts, that you may not deny Christ; he that hath not learnt to deny himselfe, the first tentation that comes, will put him upon the denyall of Christ.</p>
               <p>Now to deny our selves, is to renounce every thing in the habit of our heart, that comes in competition with the Lord and a good conscience, that when either that enjoyment must be left or a good conscience, we are content to let that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment goe rather then a good Conscience. This was the frame of <hi>Moses</hi> spirit when he saw the treasures and pleasures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and a good conscience could not be held together; upon deliberation hee chose to suffer affliction with Gods people. So the three Children when they could not hold their lives and a good conscience, were content to be cast into a fiery Furnace. When one told <hi>Luther</hi> that the truth could not be preached without offending the Priests, he made this answer, <hi>Ego obtuli me, &amp;c.</hi> I have offered up my selfe in the name of the Lord, his will be done, what sayes he, they will kill me? Well, they will not raise mee up againe, that they may kill me againe, they will defame me for an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick? Well, Christ was counted with the wicked.</p>
               <p>Perhaps thou spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s at Idolatry, but whatsoever thou holdst when Gods calls for it, thou makst an Idoll of it; <hi>Asa</hi> had made an Idol of his mother, had he not deposed her for set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up an Idol in a grove. No doubt would <hi>Micaiah</hi> have prophesied as the other Prophets did, and have spoken well to King <hi>Ahab,</hi> and would the <hi>Baptist</hi> have been sparing in urging the seventh Commandement, they might have beene great with their respective Princes; but when God put them upon a businesse that would hazzad all, they feared not to tel their Princes those things from God, which doubtlesse they
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119464:31"/> did forsee, would at last, procure the bread and water of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
               <p>I am sure there was nothing so deare to the Lord, but he parted with it for his people, he had but an only begotten Son that lay in his bosome, and he emptied him of his glory, and parted with him for us, and should we not part with all that we have for him, Besides, those things which Saints have habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually parted with for Christ, how oft hath God given them again to them with advantage; so Queene <hi>Ester</hi> left her life, if I perish, I perish, and the three Children who chose a fiery Furnace, rather then Idolatrous worship, God gave them all their lives again, and preferment to boote. <hi>Abraham</hi> lest all he had for God, yea, his dear Sonne <hi>Isaac,</hi> and God multiplied all that he had, <hi>Moses</hi> left the Court of a Prince for God, and in time he might have been King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and God made him after the Prince of his people, <hi>Joseph</hi> left a plentifull house for a good Conscience, and God intreated him kindly in prison, and after raised him to great preferment in <hi>Pharohs</hi> Court; perhaps he will not thus exalt thee (for as the way of his judgements are unsearchable, so are the wayes of his mercy) yet are sundry of his Children so exalted, and for thy part thou mayst make full account of peace of Conscience, and his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed shining face which are an abridgement of all other bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings.</p>
               <p>Experience tells us, when Gods people part with any thing for God, God makes it up with better then they forgoe; for example, he makes up losse of liberty, with liberty of Conscience, poverty with riches of faith, <hi>Ruth</hi> left her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Moah</hi> for Religion, and God gave her a plentifull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state by her Marriage with <hi>Boas:</hi> the Apostles suffered paine when they were whipt, and God made it up with the joy of the Holy-Ghost, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41. In civill dealings we count it wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to put our mony or land to the greatest improvement, there is no way so to improve an estate or life, as to leave it for Christ, for so it shall be saved, in li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> whereof we shall have peace on earth, and glory in heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d what though carnall reason, that bitter enemy of God, laugh at these things, yet as it was never able to find out the truth of God, so was it never able to judge of them, yet should it be the noble disposition
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119464:32"/> of Christians to call back their mindes from their sences, and so much the more in that we have Christ his expresse word, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10 39. <hi>He that saveth his life shall loose it, and he that looseth his life for my sake shall find it;</hi> wherein Christ speakes after the manner of the world, who when they have kept their lands, liberties, and lives, though it be with the wounding of their Consciences, and complyance to all abominations of false Doctrine and false Worship: they say such a man hath saved his land, liberty, or life; to this Christ saith, have they saved them? well, but they shall loose them eternally on the other side; when Gods faithfull servants forsake their estates, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, relations, or lives for Christ, the world thinks such men are fooles, they have lost fine accomoditions, great revenews, rich trades, and which is more, their precious life; well, saith Christ, have they so lost them as you think? nay, saith Christ, you are deceived; for they shall find them for ever.</p>
               <p>On the other side take a man that to save his living or life, hath denyed the faith, and Ship-wrackt his Conscience, what is that can give him peace? other wants may be helped, as poverty by contribution, imprisonment by enlargement; but nothing can salue this malady, but the blood of Christ, and an habituall disposition to confesse what we have formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed. Besides, what is become of <hi>Demas</hi> his goods, which he gained or saved,<note place="margin">In Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nops.</note> when he forsooke Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and became a Priest of the Heathen Gods at <hi>Thessolonica,</hi> as <hi>Dorotheus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports; what is become of their livings which were gained or saved in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, by denying the truth, are they not all or most turned to dust; but what the Martyrs lost, they have found it in Heaven: If the Phisitian bid us leave such meate or drink, because he hath seene our water, or felt our pulse, we obey him, and shall we not (when God who hath felt the everlasting pulse, doth so command) leave such enjoyments as he would have us to leave, especially seeing he knowes such a thing would not in that condition be good for us.</p>
               <p>Sweet is that disposition when the Soule will not part with God for price, but is willing to go to prison, or to death with him, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. as that Martyr who s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id, though he could not dispute, yet could he dye for Christ; for want of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119464:32"/> which conclusion, when temporall hazards, or outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquishments come, many fall off and are offended at such wayes and truthes as formerly they received with great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, and fall to dispite those who first put them upon such hazardous courses, as their hearts are unwilling to close with. But Christians whose hearts are perfect, resolve, as that Martyr <hi>Iohn Araley, Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon. vol.</hi> 3. p. <hi>If every haire of my head were a man, it should suffer death in the faith</hi> I <hi>now stand:</hi> let us in the Lords strength with him resolve, I have an honour, an estate, a life; but had I an hundred of every sort, they should all pack for Christ, God forbid that I should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in anything more, or in any thing equall with him who is my love.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But if this be our duty, that we must habitually denye our selves in all for the Lord, what is the reason, persons are so unwilling to part with their enjoyments, when God and a good Conscience call for them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> There are many causes hereof, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. A placing of anall-sufficiency in whole or in part,<note place="margin">Animus per omnes mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di partes commeans alque dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusus, ex quo anima quae nas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt. Saltria lib. 4de gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bern. dciex Pithagora,</note> in the comforts and creatures here below, so that as the ancient hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens made Gods of their Garlick, Onions, Hearbes, Plants, Fruites, not so much in respect of these things themselves, as if they thought them to be Gods; but because they thought God to be an universall spirit, partially subsisting in them; so most men think part of their comfort to be in the things of this world, and that it cannot be had else-where, save in them; and hence they will not forgoe them: whereas there is no comfort in any creature but is more eminently in God, as whatsoever is in the effect, is virtually in the cause; whatsoever sweetnesse or comfort is in Wife, Children, or Estates, is much more in God, else could not the Saints have these things when they are in prison, and in the middst of persecution, as <hi>Mark</hi> sets down they have, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.30.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The second cause is want of assurance of a better happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, the soule of man claspes fast hold of happinesse, either true or apparant, like men upon the point of drawing whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they lay hold of, they will not let it go; naturally men are loath to let go their present happinesse how low soever, till they be sure of a better; a servant will not willingly part with
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119464:33"/> a bad service, till he be sure of a better master, were a man as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured that God had pardoned his sins, and accepted him in Christ, he would say, let an Estate, Friends, Countrey, and all go, so that I may win Christ; besides, nothing doth so weaken the spirit of a man in paint of confession of truth, as feare of Hell, a man reasons thus, if I confesse such and such truthes, I may be put in prison, and so kept, or scanted from outward comforts, which would continue my life, or the Magistrate m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y put me to death, and so though I am not assured to go to Hell, yet am I also not assured to go to Heaven; hence persons are fearfull in confession of what they know; but when a man is assured that God is his God, and his sins pardoned in Christ, he is bold in confession, he knowes the worst that men can do is only to kill the body, which the persecutor in so doing shall the sooner send his soule into Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third cause is suspition of future events, men sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that it will not be good for them to be changed from an high condition to a low, we doubt poverty will be an insup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable burden, in that we shall be brought under the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable succour of others reliefe, so to loose our credit, or suffer imprisonment we doubt will not be good, yet mayst thou conclude that all will be for thy good: so that looke, as when it is night we are certain the next day the Sun will arise, though we know not whether out of a cloud, or in a bright skye, yet this we know that the Sun will arise, so may we conclude, that every event that befalles us, will be for our good, though we cannot tell how God will so dispose it, and this conclusion is drawn from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>all is yours, whether P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul, Apollos, or Cephas, or life, or death,</hi> &amp;c. that is, all is ours in reference to our enjoyment of God in Heaven, also <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. all things work together for good to them that love him.</p>
               <p>The Saints of God that have learnt to denye themselves, do duty without suspition what the issue will be. <hi>Abraham</hi> when he went from his Countrey, he knew not whither he went, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8. yet he obeyed God; <hi>Gideon Iude</hi> 6.25. God bad him throw down the Altar of <hi>Baal,</hi> and cut down the Grove which was by it, he might have reasoned, if I do this thing, the men of the City being worshippers of <hi>Baal,</hi> will put m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to death, and indeed they had like to have done it, vers. 30. for they bad <hi>Joash</hi> bring out his son <hi>Gideon,</hi> that he may dye,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119464:33"/> because he hath cast downe the Altar of <hi>Baal,</hi> but <hi>Gideon</hi> did his duty without suspecting of the issue. So <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 1.15. <hi>When it pleased God who seperated him from his mothers wombe to reveale his Sonne in him, that he might preach him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heathen,</hi> he saith immediatly, <hi>I consulted not with flesh and blood,</hi> as if he should say, flesh and bloud would have told me, the event would be dangerous, the preaching of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus might cost me my life; but he considered what he had in command from God, without once questioning what the issue would be. Which is a good patterne for us, when God puts us upon any hazardous duty, to shut our eyes and eares to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reason: carnall reason teaches to consider what the issues and events of things be, and so draw the Scriptures to speak according to their mindes; and hence is it, that most people in <hi>Spaine</hi> are Papists, in <hi>Switzerland</hi> are <hi>Calvinists,</hi> in <hi>Saxony</hi> are <hi>Lutherans,</hi> in <hi>Scotland, Presbiterians,</hi> in <hi>New England, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants, &amp;c.</hi> because, though in sundry of these places there be many good men, yet the flesh in them, as well as the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reason in wicked men foresees, that if they be other then so, the Countrey will not beare them, or not with a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table respect; and hence, though not without much difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they labour to bundle the truth, and the times together, and draw the Scripture to speak according to the respective Common-wealth wherein the lines of the temporall enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are fallen our to them: the root of a great part of this is the suspition of a good issue, should they swerve from the present course of that tenent, which in that Countrey doth at present prevaile. And hence it is, that there is in many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, though not in all, such a conformity in Religion, so that mostly what Religion the Master is of, all his children &amp; servants are of the same, because the flesh in them silently rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; that if the wife should go from her husbands religion, or the Child from his Father, or the servant from his Master, they doubt the husband, father, or master, would not like it, and what the issue of such a persons displeasure will be, they know not, but hereof they are very suspicious, that the event will not be good to them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth cause why persons are so loath to part with their enjoyments, when God and Conscience call for them,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119464:34"/> is the beholding of good and evill things, in the divels per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective glasse; if a man be to leave an estate for God, Satan well let us see the benefit of it, what an happinesse it is to live of a mans selfe without being beholden to others, hee will tell you, that titles, without Proportionable estates, fall under the miserable succour of other mens Pitie; he will let you see the benefit of an estate both for dyet and apparell, and many other wayes, though in the meane time he will conceal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the cares and feares that attend it, and the future account; so for honour, he will let men see, what it is to have respects, salutes, observancies, but conceales the burthens that accompany it, as envy, pride, &amp;c. the like he doth for sensuall pleasures. Contrarily, if a man be to suffer any thing for Christ, let Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan alone to make it terrible, as if it be poverty, he lets us see the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st miserable spectacles, which perhaps Gods curse for sinne, not his crosse for triall, hath so afflicted; if it be banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he shewes us the excellency of our Native soile; he will lay before us the trouble of going to a people whose language we know not, and the danger of sicknesse, by the change of ayre and diet, he will tel thee, that though thou be never so conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, yet among strange people thy honesty will be questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. If it be imprisonment, he will set before thee the bad ayre, the lothsome smels, the churlishnesse and extortion of Gaolers, the nastinesse of thy lodging, and the losse of all thy emploiments in thy particular calling, besides the changeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of imprisonment, for dyet and otherwise; now persons seeing these and many other good and evill things, as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill presents them, they are apt to startle backe at the first noise of sufferings.</p>
               <p>Against all Satans goods which he shall propose, oppose the peace of Conscience in present, and the Crowne of glory in future, we shall have in the things we forgoe; and against all his evils, oppose the deniall of Christ to those that deny him, and that worme of Conscience, which together with a fire that will never goe out, will gnaw upon the fearefull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all eternity, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8. Besides, its our wisdome not to consider of good or evill things what they are now in present, but what they will be in future; what will wealth and honour (which Satan so magnifies) stand in the stead,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119464:34"/> when thou shalt appeare before the Tribunall of Christ, what will imprisonment hurt thee, when thou shalt enjoy the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberties of the children of God, what will poverty, banishment, death, hurt thee, when thou shalt have the riches of glory, with life everlasting in thine owne countrey.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth cause is mis apprehension about the things of this life, as we think to finde content in them; but who hath found it? did <hi>Ahab</hi> in his Vineyard, <hi>Haman</hi> in honour, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> in beauty, there is a vaste disproportion betwixt these, and the soule of man, content arises from God, not from goods, when he comes into the soule, then the soule is full, and not till then: and whereas men imagine some continued succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of earthly things, how are they deceived, fire: water, suretiship, warre, doe often strip the most wary men; how oft doth death strip thee of a friend in whom all thy hope was; how often doth a small moment of time swallow up all thy pleasures, consider these earthly things can neither preserve that life we have, nor give us that life we want; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever we have in this life, is but an apparision or fashion which passeth away, as the saluting Traveller on the high way whom we never see more, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> But how many I get an habit to deny all for the Lord, and a good Conscience, that so I may nor deny Christ for the saving of any earthly thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. Apprehend Gods love to thy soule in his Sonne, in that there was nothing too good for us, but that he gave his dearely beloved Sonne for us; hee or shee to whom much is forgiven, the same loveth much, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.47 and this hee did when we were enemies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. We love him, and cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently bring forth the fruits of love, <hi>because he first loved us,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4 19 This love of God is seen not onely in giving his Sonne, but himselfe to us as an husband, as the husband loves all in the Familie, but gives himselfe to his wife; so God b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowes his Sunne to shine, and raine to fall on the wicked, but he gives himselfe to every godly soule, as an husband to his sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>use. Upon the souls apprehension hereof, the soule like a loving and dutifull spouse, gives up its will, and all that it hath to the Lord. So that as in civill marriage the husband en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes the wife with a state of participation in all that hee
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119464:35"/> hath, and the wife gives up not onely h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r will, but her porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him: So in spirituall marriage Christ endowes the soule with a state of participation in what he hath, and the soule gives up all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at it hath to the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Get a soveraigne love to God, this is the most prime ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, if not a concomitant of justifying faith, which I rather thinke, whatsoever we love besides the Lord, unlesse it be in subordination to him, either actually, when we particularly thinke of it, or habitually in the generall constant purpose of our minds, we love it in opposition unto him, that is, he will interpret such a neglect as an opposition. Hence were those commands. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.27. The Sonnes of <hi>Levi</hi> who were on the Lords side, <hi>vers.</hi> 26. and so were not guilty of the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Calve-worship (<hi>For all were not guilty,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7.) were commanded by <hi>Moses</hi> from God, to slay every man his brother, and every man his companion, and every man his neighbour who had been the prime actours about the golden Calfe; doubtlesse, this was grievous to them, but God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring it, and they (knowing that when the love of God, and the love of a brother cannot stand together, the love of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is to be cast <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff, that the love of God may take place) obeyed God and <hi>Moses,</hi> and slew about thee thousand men. Such was that Command, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. <hi>If thy brother, the son of thy mother, or thy son, or thy daughter, or the wife of thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, or thy friend, which is as thine owne soule, entise thee se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, saying let us go s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rve other gods,—th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u shalt not consent unto him, neither shall thine eye pity him, neither shalt thou spare, neither shalt thou conceale him, but thou shalt surely kill him, thy hand shall be fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st upon him, &amp;c.</hi> All which proves, that the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate love we have to any creature, ought to give place to that Soveraigne l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve we have to God. Such a love we have in <hi>Eli,</hi> to the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.9. <hi>Who said unto his father and his mother, I have not seene him</hi> (concluding both under the more worthy gender) <hi>neither did hee acknowledge his brethren, nor knew his owne children;</hi> that is, hee was so impartiall in his Gods cause (in destroying the principall actors in the Calve-worship, which even now I mentioned) that hee did not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge either father or mother, brother or sister, or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, against Gods Commands.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119464:35"/>
               <p>From this Soveraign love to God sprang those couragious selfe-denialls of the Martyrs, we must not think they had bodies of brasse, or muscles of steele, or that they were not as sensible of torment as others; but as the heate of a fever dryes up outward vlcers, or as the heate of a fire swallowes up the heate of a fever, so the love of God in the Martyrs surmounting their love to all other things, did swallow up their love to their wives and Children, yea, to their own lives, so that they thought them not too good for God.</p>
               <p>Indeed we may love these comforts, but not above the Lord, 'not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 10.37. <hi>He that loveth Father or Mother more then me, is not worthy of me, and he that loveth Son or Daughter more then me, is not worthy of me,</hi> that is, I will not accept him, I will not think him worthy of me; we may love the comforts here below with a love in the second place, as a husband will allow that his wife love her friends with an inferiour love, only the prime love must be kept for him; nor will it be sufficient that she love her husband better then many thousands, if there be one placed in her affections before him; so it will not be sufficient that we love the Lord better then many things, but we must love him better then every thing, that is, habitually leave all for the Lord.</p>
               <p>Many men that love the world, would part with much for the Lord, even out of selfe love to their soules, only they would have so much as would secure them against time and chance, as <hi>Ananias</hi> &amp; <hi>Saphira;</hi> but when they must part with all in the bent of their hearts, they go away sorrowfull, as the young man did; many are so taken up with a convenient house, that they will rather part with Christ and Heaven then it, others are so hemd in with friends and allyance, that come what will come, they will not leave them; but Christ saith, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. <hi>if any man come to me, and hate not his Father and Mother, and Wife and Children, and Brethren and Sisters, yea and his own life also, he cannot be my Disciple,</hi> which is not meant simply that we should hate them, for we are commanded to love our enemies, much more friends, and such near friends as Father and Mother most; but we are to hate them if they come in competition with the Lord. It is with the soule in this point, as with a Tenant, who is bound to pay so much rent upon the forfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a rich Lease; if the Tenant at the pay day should bring three quarters of his mony, the Landlord will not receive it, he will
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119464:36"/> not receive a penny of it if the whole be not brought: so the debt the soul is obliged in to God is a soveraign love, if we bring not that, the Lord will not receive any at our hands, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37.38. Christ saith, <hi>Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind, this is the first and great Commandemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the meaning is, we are not to love the Lord sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately as a Creature, but soveraignly as a Creator: such a disposition was in <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3.7.8. and those <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11. unlesse this soveraign love be wrought in the soul, it were easie for a des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate fellow, meeting a man in a corner, to make him forsweare Jesus Christ, and to worship <hi>Mahomet</hi> for the saving of his life.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To leave all for the Lord, get a disposition not only to give a lift at the Crosse, but also take up every Crosse that comes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thee and duty; many men give a lift at this or that Crosse, but finding the weight of it, they lay it down again, and wil not take it up; for example, this, or that person were going in such a way, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the dictate of the Conscience, when they begun in it, they thought their friends would be a little offended at it, and that it wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d be some dammage to them in their calling, and that they were willing to undergo; but when they see, that if they go on in such wayes, their friends will wholly cast them off, and that they are like to suffer the totall losse of their calling, and be forsed to se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke a new one, then they begin to question, and in a short while to cast off the things they have formerly acknowledged for preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous truthes: one mans crosse that God layes on him is poverty, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others, imprisonment, anothers, disinheriting, anothers is losse of calling, anothers is displeasure of friends and kindred, certainly, let the Crosse be what it will be, though never so heavie, even to the losse of life, we must not only give a lift at it, but we must take it up, we need not create Crosses to our selves; for if we live godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will find us out, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>whosoever will live godlily shall suffer persecution,</hi> only we are to take, up them that God layes on us. Instancies hereof are <hi>Paul,</hi> when the spirit told him, that bonds and afflictions in every City did abide him, he would not refraine from his duty, none of these things, saith he, move me, so I may fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish my course with joy, <hi>Acts</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.13. hence the Saints of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35.36, 37. <hi>Some of them endured bonds and imprisonment, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were tortured, others had tryall of cruel mockings and scourg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119464:36"/> others were stoned, others wandered about in Sheepe-skins and Goat-skins, being destitute, afflicted, tormented:</hi> to shew that Gods p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ple (of whom the world was not worthy) did not all of them suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the same Crosse, though all of them had the same habits and dispositions to have suffered, but each of them tooke up that Crosse, that lay betwixt them and their duty.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Consider, thy heart is not perfect with the Lord, till thou com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st to a disposi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, to let go every thing for the Lord, looke under the whole Heaven, if there be any thing thou wilt not forsake, or any thing thou wilt not suffer for the Lord, thy heart is not perfect with God, its a mistake in men to think that to love the Lord more then our estates or lives, proceedes not from the na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure of saving faith, simply considered; but from some emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent degree of it, seeing that Christ saith, <hi>Luke</hi> 14 33. <hi>whosoever he be that forsaketh not all that he hath, he cannot be my Disciple,</hi> that is, if thou beest borne to a thousand pound lands a yeare, yet if God, and a good Conscience, to witnesse the truth call for it, thou must forsake it, so <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.17. Christ saith, <hi>If thou wilt be perfect, sell all that thou hast and give to the poore, and thou shalt have treasure in Heaven,</hi> were Christ now on earth, he might say as much to any man, and we were bound upon paine of salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to obey him. Papists abuse this, and such like places, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming voluntary poverty to be one of the 3. estates of perfection, expound it thus, that he that will live a most happy life, must give all his goods to the poore, and come and live in a cloyster, as one <hi>Francis Sanguinetis,</hi> formerly a Fryar of <hi>Millaine</hi> told me; but the meaning is, that if thou wilt assure thy selfe that thy heart is perfect with God, thou must be content to part with thy estate when the Lord calles for it; so God judged of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that his heart was perfect in that he thought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing too good for God, no not his dear <hi>Isack, Gen.</hi> 22.16. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Neh.</hi> 9 8. these thoughts, if well meditated of, would much abase us, and keepe us from contemning any man for his meane condition in the world; for thou knowest not how soone a good Conscience may bring thee in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the like c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dition, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> actually poore, and thou art habitually; they have nothing now, and God knowes how soone thou shalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave nothing hereafter: certainly, to have these loose and dying affecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns to he enjoyments of the world, are greater mercies then the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119464:37"/> themselves, and what I say of estate, I affirme the same of life, thy heart is not perfect with God if thou hast not a disposition to lay it down for a good conscience: we will not speak of Infants (the way of whose salvation is to us unknown) none are sav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d but Martyrs, either actuall or habituall, having faith enough to encourage them, and love to constraine them to be Martyres, yea even those that shun persecution by flight, fly with this intention to suffer the greatest extremity in the world if they be taken, rather then to deny the Lord, or any part of his truth; which disposition being fixed and rivited in the soule, its lawfull for us when we are persecuted in one city to fly unto another, as Christ permits us, <hi>Math.</hi> 10.23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But is not all flight unlawfull from these Commands of Christ, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.26, 27. and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> 1. Christ fled from <hi>Herod,</hi> and from those that would have killed him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.30. 2. We may flye with a minde not to live to our selves, but to God, we must not tempt God by exposing our selves to needlesse dangers; <hi>Paul</hi> fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let downe by the walles of <hi>Damascus, Act.</hi> 9.25. and Christ fled, <hi>for his houre was not yet come;</hi> nay, flight is a kind of protesting against common errours, and so many hundreds, that sled into <hi>Germany</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, and many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands that fled into <hi>New-England,</hi> in our times, have borne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse against the Idolatries and Superstitions of the severall ages, onely if God do not open a doore for us, we must not flye. This was the case of the three Children, had they had the same op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity that <hi>Paul</hi> had, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.10. that any godly brethren would have sent them out of the danger, its probable they would have gone before their apprehention; if some heroicke instinct of the Spirit had not put them upon tarrying to protest against such grosse Idolatry. The two commandements of slight from one City to another, and of not fearing them that kill the body are both in one Chapter, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28. To shew that sometimes one of them may take place, and sometimes another. It is not lawfull to flye, when the truth is like to be hazarded or dishonoured by our flight, when God cuts of lawfull meanes of flight, when he shuts every dore against flight, or that we be in hold by the command of a Lawfull Magistrate; or when thy life is particularly aymed at, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.24. For so the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies power is appeased, and thou maist live to honour God in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119464:37"/> some other place, nor the soules of them will be hazarded by thy slying with the contrary to those forementioned. In these cases I suppose flight is lawfull, provided that thou fly with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named disposition, rather to dye a thousand deaths if thou beest taken, then deny thy dearest Lord, or his truth. But if there bee none of these cases, or thou beest hamperd in by relations of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or of duty to Father, Master, &amp;c. or God call thee out to suffer death, that thou canst not with good conscience avoid it, or if when thou hast opportunity of flight, but woulst not take it, but art confident, that God will not onely keepe thee from abjuration or denyall of his truth, but will also assist thee in the sealing the truth with his bloud, goe on in Gods strength herein, feare not them that can kill the body, and afterwards can doe no more, thou doest not sinne herein, but doest an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on most praise-worthy in the sight of God, Angels, and men, far beyond all the victories of <hi>Alexander, Caesar,</hi> and all the great warriours of the world.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That we may get an habit to deny all for the Lord, let us cleave unto God with stedfastnesse and resolvednesse. <hi>Daniel</hi> was purposed in his heart, though it is cost him his life, or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, not to defile himselfe with the portion of the Kings meat, <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.8. The like purpose he had, <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.10. when he knew the writing was signed, that hee that asked any Petition of God for 30 dayes, should be cast into the Lyons den, yet he held his purpose still to pray. <hi>Barnabas</hi> exhorts the Brethren, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.23. <hi>That with purpose of heart they would cleave to the Lord,</hi> that though Persecutors threatned pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sons, and whippings, and fire, and faggot, yet that (their purposes of heart cleaving to God,) they would not deny him.</p>
               <p>This is the nature of Christian resolution that it chooses that which the spirit reveales to the understanding to be good, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all oppositions that comes betwixt, when credit, and profit, and vaine feares, put in and suggest that the witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of such truths may cost you all that you have, resolution in a Christian answers all, it matters not though I lose these sweet morfels, so I can retaine God and a good Conscience; tell not me of the difficulty of the way, onely let me know which is the way, I am resolved to follow the Lambe whithersoever he calls me, I know there is no threatning so terrible as Gods, no
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119464:38"/> promise so sweet as Gods, no commandement so holy as Gods; therefore I am resolved to denye all enjoyments, and to expose my selfe to drink that cup, how bitter soever, which my Father shall give me to drink: thus <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zekiah</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.6. <hi>he clave to the Lord and departed not from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ollowing after him;</hi> thought he threates of such a potent Prince, as <hi>Senacherib</hi> were thun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered out against him, and death and dangers of all sorts hung over him, he might have waded out of all these himselfe in likelihood, by slight and so saved himselfe, though with the hazard of the ruine of all, but he would not, <hi>but clave to the Lord, and would not depart from following him.</hi> So <hi>David Psal.</hi> 119.31. <hi>I have stuck unto thy Testimonies,</hi> proud men greatly derided him, v. 51. <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s spoke against him,</hi> verse 23. <hi>Princes persecuted him,</hi> verse 161. <hi>yet his heart so stuck to God and his truth, that no scoffes nor perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, no not of the greatest of men, could take of his heart from confessing that which he judged to be Gods truth;</hi> and this resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his was as strong as an Oath, verse 106. <hi>I have sworne and will performe it, that I will keepe thy righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We may be in such a condition as some Christians were in <hi>Justin Martyrs</hi> time, <hi>Barchochebas</hi> Commander in chiefe of the Jewes in their revolt from the <hi>Romans,</hi> commanded to draw Christians alone to grievous punishments, unlesse they would denye and rayle upon Jesus Christ, <hi>Apol.</hi> 2. p. 57.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That we may get a right habit to deny all for the Lord, go in Gods strength; for want of this, though all the Disciples, and especially, <hi>Peter</hi> had a resolution to leave, even life and all for Christ, yet they fainted, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.29.30.31. <hi>though all should be offended yet will not I, and when Christ told him that night, he would denye him thrice, he spake the more vehemently, if I should dye with thee, I would not denye thee in any wise,</hi> likewise also said they all; here was a most strong resolution, yet going in their own strength, <hi>Peter</hi> the chiefe Champion was after startled at the voice of a damosell, and shamefully denyed Christ: the story of <hi>Pendleton</hi> and <hi>Sanders,</hi> is so often urged by all write<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that I forbeare it at large, <hi>Sanders</hi> was fearfull he should not endure the fire, the other sayes b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not fearful, thou sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> see this fat flesh s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, yet he tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was so strong in his own strength, tell away and the other was inabled by God to burne for the truth, some in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119464:38"/> Gods strength of weake were made strong, others in their own strength of strong became weake: as <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vid</hi> went against <hi>Goliah</hi> in the cause of God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.45. <hi>I come to thee in the name of the Lord of Hosts, the God of Armies, so in the power of the same God, should we go against all oppositions of men and Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. That we may leave all for the Lord, believe the promises, the beliefe of the promises goes in order before the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the duty required by God, <hi>Sauls</hi> promise to <hi>David,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat if he would bring an hundred sore-skins of the Phylistims, he should be his Sonne, and have one of his Daughters, put him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that hazardous attempt to kill so many of them, no man lookes after either poverty of spirit, or purity of heart, till he believe the promise that such persons shall be blessed; when you promise a man eighteene pence for his dayes work, the beliefe of your promise sets him upon the performance of the duty you require of him, so would you leave all for the Lord in the disposition of your hearts, believe the promises made to those who so deny themselves: now these promises are first of this life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.27.28, 29, <hi>we haue forsaken all and followed thee, what shall we have therefore:</hi> to this Christ answers, verse 29. <hi>every ene that hath forsaken Houses, or Brethren, or Sisters, or Father, or Mother, or Wife, or Children, or Lands, for my name sake, shall receive an hundred sold,</hi> that is, the joy and peace you have jn your Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, shall be an hundred times better th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the comfort of all these outward things: besides, we see by experience, that men that have lost their estates for a good Conscience, God hath made it up to them or their posterities one way or other: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when Satan objects to thee, thou wilt be cast in prison, or banished thy Countrey, or thy estate be sequestered, and thou wilt be made uncapable of any Office or dignity in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, if thou goes in such and such wayes, go not an inch from thy duty for to escape any of these evills, seeing thou shalt have an hundred fold in this present life, for that which thou forgoest for God. <hi>Luke</hi> repeates this promise, Cap. 18.28.29, 30. saving that he alters a little: there is no man that hath left House, or Parents, or Brethren, or Wife, or Children, for the Kingdom of Gods sake, who shall not receive manyfold more in this present time. Say then to thy soul, when thou art to leave thy friends, estate, and Countrey, well, I know where the comfort
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119464:39"/> of all these is, and I shall receive manifold for them in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent time, we are not much moved with the casting away of our igoods, when we have an insurance bound to make all good, this as our case with the Lord, he hath bound himselfe to make good all that we loose for him, with an overplus in this life, what if the streame be taken away, seeing the Fountain remaines; but you will say, what will become of my posterity, I shall leave them fatherlesse and helpl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse, for the joy of the Holy-Ghost, and peace of Conscience I receive from God, redounds only to my selfe: to this I answer, God stiles himself often the Father of the Fatherlesse: if of any Fatherlesse persons, then sure of those whose Parents have lost their lives, and estates, for a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, <hi>Jer.</hi> 49.11. <hi>Leave thy Fatherlesse Children, I will preserve them alive, and let thy Widdowes put their trust in me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What comfort Saints have in this life to encourage them in their forsakings for God, we see 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. <hi>as sorrowfull, yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rejoycing, as poore, yet making many rich, as having nothing, yet possessing all things; to have joy in sorrow, riches in poverty, all things in nothing are miseries to the world; yet this is the condition of Christians, they have all things, because they have him in whom are all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly, as wicked men in their most full enjoyments in this life are only seemingly happy, but really miserable, whether we looke upon their mirth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Even in laughter the heart is sorrowfull;</hi> or whether we looke upon their wealth, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 5.12, 13. <hi>Their wealth will not suffer them to sleepe, but its kept for the hurt of the honours,</hi> and God hath affixed an eternall woe upon their most happy enjoyments, <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.24, 25, 26. <hi>Woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you that are rich, woe unto you that are full, Wo unto you that laugh now, Woe unto you when all men speake well of you.</hi> So con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily the Saints of God in their greatest sufferings for Christ, are onely seemingly miserable, but really happy. I doo not goe about to comfort the Saints in suffering, that what they suffer is no suffering; but only the picture or Image of it, for I grant they are reall sufferings, and many of them so heavy that they would breake the backe of any creature, without assistance from heaven; but this I say, thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sufferings cannot make you really miserable. Perfect misery consists in seperaton from Christ, but neither famine, nakednesse, persecution, nor death can doe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119464:39"/> that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. Besides, perfect misery consists in taking away our hope, as the heathen man when he came to dye, hee cryed farewell hope; but the hope of Saints is laid up in heaven; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, perfect misery consists in holding the soule under a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall pressure, let the rage of man doe its worst, by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning perpetuall imprisonment, or death, (beyond which it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not goe) yet can it not alwaies hold the Saints under these pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, it will be with them as with Corke under water, it will in a while rise up above the water.</p>
               <p>To conclude this point, he that can be happy in reproaches, I <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. <hi>If ye be reproached for the name of Christ, happy are yee,</hi> he that can rejoyce in shame and scourgings, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41. <hi>They went away rejoycing, that they were counted worthy to suffer shame for his name,</hi> he that can be meery in darke prisons, and praise God after a sharpe scourging, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas, Acts</hi> 16.25. he that can looke upon the losse of all his goods with joy, as tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Heb.</hi> 16.34 who tooke joyfully the spoiling of their goods he is not real<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, but seemingly miserable, and really happy, which, is in briefe, a fulfilling of that promise that he that leaves any thing for Christ, shal receive manifold more in this present time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But specially, that we may leave al for the Lord, looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the eternall promise we have made to us in this case. <hi>Math.</hi> 19 29. <hi>Every one that hath forsaken houses, or brethren, —shall inherit everlasting life,</hi> Mark. 10.30. <hi>There hath no man that hath left father, or mother, or lands,— for my sake and the Gospels, but he shall in the world to come receive eternall life. Luke</hi> hath the same, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.30. Hence the Saints, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.34. did not onely suffer the spoyling of their go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds with patience, but tooke it with joy; why? because they had a better, and an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during substance in heaven. We are willing to part with a Lease for a Fee-simple, Lands, and Fathers, and Children are onely lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, Heaven is a Fee-simple. This made <hi>Abraham</hi> to forsake his Countrey, and not to have a minde to returne to it againe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he looked for a glorious Countrey which God had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, even a City which hath foundations, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10, 15, 16.</p>
               <p>It was a saying of one of the Ancients, when rewards were proffered him to renounce his faith, he answered, will you give me so much as you goe about to take from me; the like was spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by one <hi>Robert Oquer,</hi> when a Noble man offered him life and promotion, made this answer. Doe you thinke me such a foole, to change eternall things for temporary, the enjoyment of God
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119464:40"/> in heaven was that which comforts Saints in the deepest suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; Master <hi>Bradford</hi> speakes thus to his fellow-Martyr, <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Hunter, Be of good Comfort, we shall have a merry Supper, with the Lord this night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The soule of a man is of a large capacity, and of a vast wish, the things below cannot falsifie it, because the faculties of it are so large, but that inheritance will fill all the understanding with knowledge, and the will with joy, and that in so great a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, that the expectation of the Saints shall be exceeded, for <hi>he shall be adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red of them that beleeve,</hi> 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 1.16. Shall the hope of freedome carry up the minde of the Apprentice to looke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sent servitude, shall the hopes of the inheritance which is but for a few yeares, raise up the spirit of the Heire under all the servitude he undergoes in his nonage, and shall not the hope of the glorious inheritance in heaven beare up our spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits under any present pressures we do endure, or shall endure for Christ, and a good Conscience. Certainly there is no comparison betwixt present sufferings, and future glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17, 18.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That we may part with all things for the Lord, get wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nednesse of aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction to all things here below, be often putting it to thy selfe in this manner; I have my liberty, estate, and friends, for the presen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but God knowes how soone I must leave th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m for the Lord; this house may cease to be mine, this friend mine, this Country mine, and God alone knowes how soone this may be; till the childe be weaned it will not let the breast goe, but when once it is weaned, you may doe what you will with the breast, the childe cares not for it. So we find such sweet milke in the breast of the creatures, that we are very loath to let the breast of the creatures goe, but when old, we are wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to them; we say, let estates, friends, and all goe in the case of a good Conscience. The more our affections are fastned to any earthly comforts, the lesse comfort, and more bitternesse shall we finde in parting with it. So weaned was <hi>Abraham</hi> that he sojourned in the land of Promise, as in a strange Countrey, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.9. Hence, when God called him to leave his dwelling, he went to sacrifice his sonne, he was willing so to doe. So <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> left the treasures and pleasures of <hi>Egypt,</hi> because his heart was weaned unto them. Self-denying Christians should have their hearts to the world, not as their girdle that sits close to them, but as the cloake to their backe which hangs loose, and they upon every occasion can lay it by them. A man whose
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119464:40"/> heart is set upon the world, if any one aske him this question, or his owne heart either, whether will you leave all for Christ, or whether will you leave Christ and a good Conscience, rather then your patrimony? hee will forsake Christ rather then his goods, the soule of most men sits as close upon their enjoyments as <hi>Rachel</hi> did upon her Fathers Idols, but in leaning upon these, thou wilt leane upon that which cannot beare thee up. Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the rotten foundation of earthly things, is like a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture drawne upon the ice, which when the ice melts is brought to nothing.</p>
               <p>Its not a worke of one day to get the heart weaned to the world, no more then a child in one day is weaned to the breast, therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e should we ever and anone be proposing the unsatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing transitorinesse of the things we leave for God, and the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfort of a good Conscience, remembring this, that he that calls for your estate, in the witnesse of a good cause, could have taken it from you by many casualties of fire, water, sureti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If you would leave all for the Lord, resist wherein you can fleshly impediments, for the flesh will be ready by all means to hinder us from offering this Sacrifice unto God: now there are 3. wayes whereby the flesh will be ready to hinder us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By perswations and intreaties, carnall reason sayes, give a little to the times, save thy selfe and thine, so <hi>Peter</hi> to Christ, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.22. when Christ told him, he must suffer many things of the Elders, and be killed, <hi>Peter</hi> began to rebuke him, saying, <hi>be it far from the Lord:</hi> so did the flesh reason in <hi>Spira,</hi> pag. 16. when the spirit had suggested unto him to suffer because Christ his glory lay at stake, that if he went to prison or death in a good confession, an eternall reward would abide him, also the danger of scandall, losse of peace of Conscience, or if he doubted of the issue, to go away, though never so farre, rather then denye the Lord of life; but after these suggestions, the flesh begins in this manner, <q rend="margQuotes">be well advised fond man, consider reasons on both sides, and then judge, — dost thou not consider what misery this thy rashnesse will bring thee unto? thou shalt lose thy substance, got with so much care and travell, thou shalt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe the most exquisite torments that malice can devise, thou shalt be counted an heritick of all, and to close up all, thou shalt dye shamefully: what thinkest thou of the stinking Dungeon, the bloody Axe, the burning Fagot, — wilt thou bring thy
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119464:41"/> friends into danger, thou hast begotten Children, wilt thou now cut their throates, and inhumainly butcher them, which may in time bring honour to their Countrey,— go to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, weake man, freely confesse thy fault, &amp; helpe all these mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>series: he now listening to this Councell, goes to the Popes Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and confest that he was heartily sory for what was past, and humbly begged pardon for so great an offence, with many other words wherein he recanted the truth:</q> the nearer any one is unto us, the hardlier are their intreaties denyed, as of a Child, Father, Mother, none nearer then this flesh of ours, which was borne and bread with us, and therefore it is a matter of great difficulty to denye it. If it come to a point that either we must suffer or wound our Consciences, the flesh will bring many insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating arguments, are you the only q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ck sighted man, wiser then a Church or State? are there not many learned men, much more learned then thy selfe, who are otherwise minded, is not this the pride and stubbornnesse of thy heart, that thou refusest to conforme thy selfe to the common streame, dost thou not hear the cry of the vulgar, who everywhere call thee blasphemous, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, unpeaceable and schismaticall? will not all thy kindred and friends cast thee off, upon the report of this thy novelisme and faction? dost not thou feare to lose thy present, and be made uncapable of future advancement? may there not, will there not a Law come out in a moment; whereby thou wilt not only be defranchised, but also exiled from thy native Countrey? after which proposalls the flesh will fall to exhortations: Oh consider how hard persecution, imprisonment, and banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will bee: give way a little to the times, for the present, and thou mayst be a meane and instrument to a great good here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: the <hi>Jtalians</hi> have a proverb, God blesse me from my friends, and I will take heed of mine enemies; so pray to be bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed from such false friends and councellours as the flesh: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke such, as Christ did <hi>Peter, Mat.</hi> 16.23. <hi>get thee behind me Satan, for thou savorest not the things which be of God, but of men;</hi> whether it be the flesh in our own hearts, or the flesh in our friends, let us reject and resist it. A certain person perswading an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to recant the truth, told him: that he spoke it to him out of love, saith the Martyr, I confesse it; but there is somthing in you that is my enemy, meaning the flesh: thus Mr. <hi>Hooper</hi> the Martyr, when a box was brought and layd before him upon a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119464:41"/> stoole with his pardon (or at the leastwise it was fained to bee his pardon) from the Queen if he would turne, (he being now at the stake) at the sight whereof he cryed, <q rend="margQuotes">if you love my soule away with it, if you love my soule away with it, <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Mon.</hi> vol. 3. p. 154.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As in other things, as its well observed by a learned man, the flesh will be ready to hinder us, so in thee if we heare or read the reprehentions of the word, <q rend="margQuotes">it perswades us these are spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to others, if we think of Heaven, it saith, we shall come time enough thither, if thou thinkst to give alms, it saith, what, know whether I shall have need of it my selfe, if thou wouldest reprehend thy friend, it will draw thee by a cruel respect for fear of offending him, each good affection hath as it were two eares like a pot, by which the flesh and the world take hold to hinder the execution thereof.</q>
                  <hi>Moulin</hi> of the love of God, p. 92. and as in other things, so in this the flesh strives to hinder; there are two wayes whereby we part with enjoyments, 1. as a sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and so <hi>Abraham</hi> parted with his Sonne, and so many of the Martyrs that had opportunity of slight, who tarried to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nesse the truth, and gave their lives to the flames for it. 2. as a tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or snare, as <hi>Moses</hi> left <hi>Egypt,</hi> because there was no ayre for a good conscience to breath in; in both these, the flesh is apt to hinder, if we go to sacrifice any thing to God in point of duty, how doth the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sh pull back the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st, see it in <hi>Peter, Iohn</hi> 21 18. <hi>when thou shalt be old thou shalt stretch forth thy hands (meaning upon the Crosse) and another shall gird thee, and carry thee whither thou wouldest not,</hi> this spake he, signifying by wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> death he should glory God, though he had will enough to bring him to Martyrdom, else could he have glorified God; yet was there some avexsation and hanging back in the will, in that he was carryed whither he would not; so when earthly enjoyments are snares, and we cannot keepe in with them and duty, the flesh puls back: as we see in the example of that noble Marquesse <hi>Galeazius Caralliolus,</hi> who being to leave a rich Marquesdom for the Gospel <q rend="margQuotes">besides the mocks, slanders, and hatred of the world, and the chidings of his own Father <hi>Calantonius:</hi> the teares, complaines, and perswasions of his wife, as we may see in the relation of his, Chap. 6. p. 41. he had grievous combats with his own flesh, when he resolved to depart out of <hi>Jtaly,</hi> as appears Chap. 8. to think he must leave his earthly Father, or
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119464:42"/> else hee could no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have God his Father, that he must leave a wife so beautifull, wise, and modest, and that for ever; to leave her so full of sighes and s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bs after his departure: and besides this, to leave six small Children, who by his departure should lose all, or a great part of their honour and wealth, to leave all of them confounded together in heapes of griefe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the losse of his inheritance, and the dilica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Countrey of <hi>Jtaly;</hi> surely in the forsaking of all these, the flesh had many a pull back, and besides, Chap. 9. the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh affrighted him in this purpose of leaving all, setting before his eyes the infamy, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and other miseries, which in this his new profession, he was like to undergo; but having the Crown of glory, and such like objects before his eyes, he being assisted by the power of God, went from <hi>Italy,</hi> and lived a private life at <hi>Geneva.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Take we heed of the perswasions of our flesh, for if once it hath got us to prefer one thing before the Lord, it will on upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: do therefore herein as you do with Petitions, you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to grant, you answer them at first with an angry coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The flesh hinders us from deniall of our selves by distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. A man that is resolved to hold his estate, liberty, and life, come what will come, never wants a distinction to mock the Lord with; so the Circumcision teachers at <hi>Galatia, Gal.</hi> 6.12. <hi>As many as desire to make a faire shew in the flesh, these constraine you to be circumcised, onely lest they should suffer perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for the crosse of Christ:</hi> they did not see but that to avoid persecution, and to please the Jewes that were allyed to them in the flesh, they might preach circumcision, being they did it <hi>pro abundanti cautel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> for the greater surenesse, not intending to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow Christ, the faith of Christ crucified was not then the object of persecution, but the doctrine of the Law abolished, or to be abolished by Christ his death, for the stablishment of which law still, and that they might glory in their Proselites flesh when they came among the Jewes, that they had so migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily promoted the Jewish religion, they urged the <hi>Galatians</hi> to be circumcised, though they coloured it over by pretences of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine institution, and identity of the new covenant under the Gospel, as under the Law, or with pretences and distinctions of such like sort.</p>
               <p>So in the former times, those that bowed before the Altar to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119464:42"/> cleere themselves from Idolatry, they alledged they worshipped God in heaven, and there they terminate it; but if we begin it on earth with reverence, or reference to any creature which God hath not appointed; is it not Idolatry acccording to the plain word? which is a worshiping of God in similitudes: or if we go to God through any creature, when himself is, and ought to be the immediate object of worship, is not it Idolatry?</p>
               <p>Many men that have great lands and livings alledge, that flight in times of persecution is unlawfull, not that they intend to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse Christ by suffering; but they intend to save their estates by complying to common error. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in his booke of flight which he sent to the brethren of <hi>Luca,</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Compares these to wrangling Lawyers that pretend a zeale of justice, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hot for their Clyents, when in the meane time they make justice serve their own ends: so these men when they dare not shew themselves in the defence of the faith, and are loath to suffer slight or banishment, being held with the chaines of their estates, are glad of any pretensive arguments to prove flight un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</q> And in our times, how did many persons delude themselvs and others by these fleshly destinctions? some persons abhord the Ceremonies, yet without the practise of them they could not injoy their livings, nor perhaps civill immunities, yet would they practise what their heart disavowed, or at least doubted of, because as they pretended, they should else loose their ministry: so when superstitious Ceremonies were vrged, as bowing at the name of Iesus &amp;c. To keepe off conscience on the one side, and the crosse of Christ on the other, they held these things to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and authority commanding them to become necessary; other distinctions were then in use of Ceremonies enjoyned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the word, and against the word; those that were besides the word, it was a ruled case in those times that they might be used in the worship of God; for the Sirplice they did not wear it for signification, but for comlines, and for the signe of the crosse they did not make it operative and effective as the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists</hi> did, but only significative: not as a signe betwixt God and the child, but betwixt the Minister, people, and child, that it will answer both in belief and life what they hoped of it. Dr. <hi>Sparkes</hi> brotherly perswasions <hi>pag.</hi> 18. 23. 24. also <hi>pag.</hi> 25. he saith, if the living among <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> were a warrant for the use of the crosse, among the ancient fathers: why not for us living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119464:43"/> so many Atheists; these and many such destinctions were coyned in those times, which made a faire shew in the flesh, but had no truth. The roote of the matter was, that if they could not conforme them to the 3 innocent Ceremonies (as they were called) there was no preferment to be had for these men in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by which they meant the Kingdom. Hence to escape the crosses of poverty and of dangers on the Sea, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her losses which would befall those that travailed into forraign parts; the Devill &amp; flesh coyned these, and thousands of such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions. Should the times whirle about to the like Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, I doubt not but the flesh would play his part ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine, by the like distinctions.</p>
               <p>When men come to be put upon tryall of leaving their estates, or Countey, not one of many will reason with their consciences concerning points so hazardous; of those that do reason, not one of many will suffer conscience to speak out; but stop their eyes and eares against the whispering light of conscience, and of those that do suffer conscience to speak out, how few are they who choke it not with a cunning distinction? especia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly if it be in a case wherein some great preferments must be lost, or some great hardships suffered; how witty is the flesh to invent a self-decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving distinction? how is the conscience rackd upon the very ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terhooks in such cases. This hath been the practise of the flesh in all times where there hath been hazard of sufferings; in <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> time the calve-worship then had many distinctions to make people conforme, as though it was not at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> yet it was at <hi>Bethel</hi> whore God appeared to <hi>Iacob.</hi> Besides we worship not the calves as they, <hi>Psa.</hi> 106.19. But God in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m: so the popish di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions of principal &amp; secondary head, Mediators of red mpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; intercession, a propitiatory sacrifice of bloudy &amp; unbloudy, and the present distinctions of these times, which in sundry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies are used (which for some reasons I shall be silent to take into) cease not to preach un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o us (besides the experience of our owne carnall hearts) that whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y thing is to be forsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or suffered for a good conscience, the flesh is proue to put the soul upon distinctions to escape the cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sse, &amp; obtain the benefit. And hence it is, that men can with ease passe out of one Religion into another, altering their Religion in part, or in whole, with as little difficulty as they doe the fashion of their apparell.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119464:43"/>3. The flesh goes about to hinder us from deniall of our selves by proffers of enjoyments, if thou wilt do thus thou shalt live in honour and credit, as the Devill said to Christ, all these things will I give thee if thou wilt fall downe and worship me; so the flesh saith, all this shalt thou have if thou wilt but doe as others doe: Thus when <hi>Balaam</hi> knew the mind of God that he should not curse his people, the flesh hearing of gold and promotion that <hi>Balaak</hi> would give him, though he had a flat deniall from God in the thing, would venture, though not to curse them, yet to teach them a tricke that would cause Gods anger to break in, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.24. compared with <hi>Num.</hi> 24. the flesh like <hi>Nebuchadnezar Dan.</hi> 3. sets up a golden Imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and all men fall downe to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, except the servants of God: in these cases consider what the flesh goes about to take from you, instead of what it gives you, it proffers you wealth, and takes away an eternall treasure, proffers you liberty, and enthralls your conscience, proffers you temporall life to deprive you of that which is eternall.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The flesh goes about to hinder us from deniall of our selves, by presenting unto us objects of feare and terrour: what though thou despisest preferment, art thou able to combate with prisons, death, fire, and fagot? the Devill and the flesh put that question, that Christ put to the mother of <hi>Zebedees</hi> sons, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Art thou able to drinke of the cup that I sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> drinke of?</hi> Dost thou not consider how cruell the Adversaries will be to thee when they have thee in their owne power? here Satan and flesh will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent all things in the most formidable manner, to stop us, if it be possible, in a Christian course: let us not feare these objects, but imitate M. <hi>Rogers,</hi> the first Martyr that was burned in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days: a little before his burning his pardon was brought, if he would have recanted, but he utterly refused it; <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 131. the like is reported of M. <hi>Mantel</hi> the elder, who as he was led to execution, at his first casting under the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the rope brake: then they would have had him recanted the truth, and receive the Sacrament of the Altar, (as they term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it) and then they said, he should have the Queens pardon; but M. <hi>Mantel</hi> refused their Serpentine counsell, and chose rather to die, then to have life for dishonouring God, <hi>Acts &amp;. Mon. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 97. when the flesh makes these proposalls, art thou able to suffer this and that? answer thou as <hi>Paul</hi> did, by the power of Christ I shall be able, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. but if it aske what we will doe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119464:44"/> in case of Martyrdome, answer we, God that brings us to the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of Martyrdome, will give us the faith of Martyrs, in the mean time in the strength of God our purposes are to stand to his truth with the losse of all, by faith we stand, by faith we fight, and by faith we overcome; it's Gods work to strengthen us, it's our worke to live by faith, as <hi>Policarpus</hi> and <hi>Latimer</hi> did, both which before their sufferings professed their Beliefe, that God would not suffer them to be tempted above their abilitie: in these cases God is either wont to abate the heat, or else give his servants strength to beare it; when the Devill and flesh come with most terrour learne we to out-vie them; if they tell you of prisons, tell them how much terrible is the prison of hell, if they present the condemnation of Tribunalls, do you present that great condemnation at the great Tribunall, if they threaten you with displeasure of friends, present the displeasure of God and glorified spirits: such a combate had <hi>George Tankerfield,</hi> a little before his burning, of whom Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> saith, <q rend="margQuotes">that he sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on a forme before the fire put off his shooes, and hose, and stretch'd out his leg to the flame, and when it had touched his foot, he quickly with-drew his leg, shewing how the flesh did perswade him one way, and the Spirit another way; the flesh said, Oh thou foole, wilt thou burne and needst not? the Spirit said, be not afraid, for this is nothing in respect of fire eternall: the flesh said do not leave the company of thy friends, and acquaintance which love thee, and will let thee lack no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the spirit said, the company of Jesus Christ and his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious presence doth exceed all fleshly friends, the flesh said, doe not shorten thy time, for thou mayest live if thou wilt much longer, the spirit said, this life is nothing unto that life which is in heaven which lasteth for ever, <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 396. <hi>Hierome</hi> of Prague that famous man was not a little startled by his flesh of his proposing fears and terrours to him, having lyen a yeare lacking but seven dayes in prison in chaines, his adversaries threatning him with death, forced him to abjure and recant, and consent unto the death of <hi>John Hus,</hi> that he was justly and truly condemned and put to death by them, he for feare of death, and according to the tenour exhibited unto him, did make abjuration, renouncing the Doctrines taught by <hi>John Hus</hi> and <hi>John Wicklif,</hi> and that he did worthily judge <hi>I. Hus</hi> and his Doctrine, with his Adherents to be condemned by
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119464:44"/> the Councell as hereticall,<hi>Acts &amp; Mon. vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 833. but a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time after coming before the Councell of Constance, he retracted what he had spoke, and before the Councell affirmed <hi>Iohn Hus</hi> to be a good, just, and holy man, and much unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that death he did suffer, and that <hi>Hus</hi> and <hi>Wicklif</hi> were holy and blessed men, and after many other words he added, that all the sinnes that ever he had committed did not so much gnaw and trouble his conscience, as did that only sinne which he had committed, in that in his Recantation he had spoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that good and holy man and his Doctrine, and specially in consenting unto his wicked condemnation, concluding, that he did utterly revoke and deny that wicked Recantation hee had made in that most cursed place, and that he did it through weaknesse of heart, and feare of death; and moreover, that what thing soever he hath spoken against that blessed man, hee hath altogether lied upon him, and that he doth repent him with his whole heart that ever he did it, <hi>Acts &amp; Mon. vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 836. in which example, we see how prone the flesh is to bee startled with terrours of death, and how God by his Spirit can and doth encourage his Servants not to feare Councells or death, as we see in <hi>Hieromes</hi> valiant Confession before the Councell, whose courage was no lesse seen at the verie stake, for standing at the stake bound, the Executioner kindling the fire behind him, <hi>Hierome</hi> called to him, and bad him kindle it before his face, for (said he) I am not afraid of it; for had I, I had not come hither at this time, having had so many oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities offered me to escape it, History of modern Divines in the life of <hi>Hieron. Prag.</hi> p. 12. I will conclude with that saying of <hi>Iustin Martyr,</hi> to the encouragement of Christians, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, you may kil us, but you cannot hurt us, <hi>Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Anton. Pium,</hi> and a little after in the same place he saith, upon your inquisition we professe our selves to be Christians, knowing that the punishment of death is readie for them that doe confesse: if we expected a Kingdome on earth, we would deny that we might not be killed, and we would strive to lie hid that we might partake of our expectation, but wee have not our hope <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, upon present things, we are not in care in respect of them that kill us, especially knowing, that die we must,</q> and in the same pag. 64. he saith, the Apostles having gone from Jerusalem preached in every place, although death
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119464:45"/> was decreed against those that taught, or did at all confesse the Name of Christ, which we every where (saith he) confesse and declare; but if you as enemies will encounter with these words that are spoken, you can doe no more but (as we said before) kill us, which brings no hurt to us, but to you and to all those who doe unjustly hate us, and do not repent, it procures everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing torments in fire, Ibid. p. 64.65.</p>
               <p>And that we may not be scared with these terrors which the flesh and Devill present, let us take <hi>Tertullians</hi> counsell in this case, lib. ad Martyras C.6. <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>let us be turned to look upon the</hi> condition of man, that these things may instruct us if things are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly to be undergone of Christians, which are wont to happen to persons against their wil: how oft have burnings burnt persons alive, how oft have wild beasts comming out of their dens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured men both in the woods and in the midst of their Cities, how many are kild of theeves by the sword, of enemies by the crosse, being first tortured and reproachfully misused? if out of terror of men we shall banke our duty to God,</q> it may stand with Gods justice both to damne our soules for our fearfulnesse, and yet whether we wil or no to bring the thing that we fear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us in this present world, as he did upon a certaine Smith in <hi>Q. Maries</hi> time, who being an instrument of inlightening ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the partie inlightened being now in prison, <q rend="margQuotes">sent to know the reason why he went to Masse, and did not walke as he had taught him, to whom he answered, the things I taught you were truth; but so it is, I cannot burne: afterwards through the just hand of God this Smith was burnt in his bed.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <head>March 16. 1647.</head>
            <p>I Have perused this Treatise of the deniall of Christ, and finding it to be pious, powerfull, and verie profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in these back-sliding times, I doe allow it to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and published.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>